<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A tragedy called the Popish Plot reviv'd detecting the secret league between the late King James and the French king, the popish conspiracy to murder His present Majesty King William, and the wicked contrivance for adulterating the coin of this kingdom : with many other hellish practices : dedicated to Sir Roger L'Strange, the Fellows of St. John's College in Cambridg, non jurors, and the rest of the Jacobite crew / by a sincere lover of his countrey.</title>
            <author>Oates, Titus, 1649-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53548</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O58</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7790</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13722267</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13722267</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101573</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53548)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101573)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 846:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A tragedy called the Popish Plot reviv'd detecting the secret league between the late King James and the French king, the popish conspiracy to murder His present Majesty King William, and the wicked contrivance for adulterating the coin of this kingdom : with many other hellish practices : dedicated to Sir Roger L'Strange, the Fellows of St. John's College in Cambridg, non jurors, and the rest of the Jacobite crew / by a sincere lover of his countrey.</title>
                  <author>Oates, Titus, 1649-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by Titus Oates.  Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Consists primarily of extracts from Oates' letters, testimony, and various works.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101573:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRAGEDY, CALLED <hi>The Popiſh Plot,</hi> REVIV'D:</p>
            <p>Detecting the SECRET LEAGUE Between the Late King <hi>James</hi> and the <hi>French King;</hi> The POPISH CONSPIRACY to Murder His preſent Majeſty King <hi>WILLIAM;</hi> And the wicked Contrivance for <hi>Adulterating the COIN</hi> of this Kingdom:</p>
            <p>With many other HELLISH PRACTICES.</p>
            <p>Dedicated to Sir <hi>Roger L'Eſtrange,</hi> the Fellows of St. <hi>John</hi>'s College in <hi>Cambridg, (Non Jurors)</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Jacobite Crew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a ſincere Lover of his Countrey.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the Author, 1696.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:101573:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101573:2"/>
            <head>To Sir <hi>Roger L'Eſtrange,</hi> the Fellows of St. <hi>John</hi>'s College, and the reſt of the Jacobite Crew.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THAT your as induſtriouſly as maliciouſly embrace every Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of venting your Selves to the Diſparagement of our Preſent happy Settlement, is undeniably evident to all Men, and hath in no particular been more manifeſt than in your cheriſhing and fomenting the loud Clamour under which the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment has of late labour'd upon the account of the <hi>diminiſhing and adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terating our Coin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Conſideration hereof led me to reflect upon what I remember I had read in Dr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s <hi>Narrative of the Popiſh Plot;</hi> and turning to it, I there find good Ground to charge to the Account of your Party, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other the manifold Evils under which the Nation groans, that which is now ſo ſenſibly felt, and highly complained of: He there told you what now to our Coſt we find fulfilled, that <hi>one Branch of that Horrid Plot was to adulterate our Money and Plate; and that to that end the Conſpirators had Bankers, Brokers, Merchants, Goldſmiths, and other Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, whom they ſtock'd and ſet up with Money of the Jeſuits Society.</hi> The Jeſuits then boaſted that they were promiſed to have the Management of the Mint, and that thereby they ſhould be made the Judges of good and bad Money, and manage the ſame to the beſt Advantage for their Cauſe.</p>
            <p>The Caſe ſtanding thus, Gentlemen, why will you be ſo vile as to criminate the Government for the Miſchief which you have brought upon your Countrey? Will you perſiſt to out-face the Sun, and term that a Sham-Plot which has ever ſince been cultivated and carried on? Conſider, I beſeech you, in how many Inſtances what was laid down in that Narrative has been verified. He there told you, that King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second <hi>was to be removed by Dagger, Piſtol or Poiſon;</hi> and, that that was effected by the laſt, is as little to be doubted, as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101573:3"/>it may now be called into queſtion, whether the Coin be <hi>adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He told you, that <hi>your Adored Duke</hi> was <hi>a Papiſt;</hi> but your Stupidity or Impudence was ſuch, that you denied it to the day that he ſtept into the Throne: Nay, not only ſo, but ſome of you in <hi>a Pack'd Jury</hi> brought in that Prince <hi>Not Guilty;</hi> and gave him the modeſt Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of 100000 <hi>l.</hi> in an Action againſt the Doctor for declaring that great Truth, then ſo highly neceſſary to be known.</p>
            <p>Nay further, he not only told, but foretold the Miſery and inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible Calamity which like a Torrent was, with that unhappy King, breaking in upon theſe poor Nations, and ready to bear down our Religion, Laws and Liberties. But this alſo was turn'd into Ridicule by that eminent <hi>Guide of the inferiour Clergy,</hi> you I mean Sir <hi>Roger,</hi> that Beautefeu of an <hi>Obſervator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore I ſhall upon this Occaſion take the Liberty to aggravate the Guilt of the unpardonable Infidelity of your Malignant Faction, in the Points before touch'd upon; and that not by urging againſt you, that what was then declared, has ſince come to paſs, but by evincing that at that very day there was laid before you irrefragable Evidence of the Truth of that happy Diſcovery: And this I partly collect from Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi>'s never to be forgotten Letters, which were never denied or ſo much as doubted; of which, to refreſh your Memories, take here a few Heads.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For my part</hi> (ſays he) <hi>I can ſcarce believe my ſelf awake, or the thing real, when I think on a Prince, in ſuch an Age as we live in, converted to ſuch a degree of Zeal and Piety, as not to regard any thing in the World in compariſon of — the Converſion of our Poor Kingdom, which hath been a long time oppreſſed and miſerably haraſſed with Hereſy and Schiſm,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now as to the <hi>Duke's</hi> being then link'd with that bloody <hi>Tyrant</hi> the <hi>French King,</hi> read <hi>Coleman</hi> again. — <hi>Knowing the Intereſt of our King,</hi> [<hi>Charles</hi> the 2d.] <hi>and in a more particular manner of my more immediate Maſter the Duke, and his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty to be ſo</hi> INSEPARABLY UNITED, <hi>that it was</hi> IMPOSSIBLE TO DIVIDE THEM, <hi>without deſtroying them all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Majeſty</hi> [the French King] <hi>was pleaſed to give order, to ſignify to his R. H.</hi> MY MASTER, <hi>that his Majeſty was fully ſatisfied of his R. H's good Intentions towards him; and that</hi> HE ESTEEMED BOTH THEIR INTE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RESTS BUT AS ONE <hi>and the ſame,</hi> [The Rooting out the Northern He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy, and enſlaving Mankind;] <hi>That my Lord</hi> Arlington <hi>and the</hi> PAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAMENT <hi>were both to be look'd upon as</hi> very unuſeful to their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101573:3"/>
            <p>—Father <hi>Ferrier</hi>—<hi>begg'd his R. H. to propoſe to his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty what he thought neceſſary for his own Concern, and</hi> THE ADVAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAGE OF RELIGION, <hi>and his Majeſty would certainly do all he could to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance both, or either of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—<hi>I communicated it to his R. H.</hi> [ſays <hi>Coleman</hi>] <hi>to which his R. H. commanded me to anſwer, as I did on the</hi> 29th <hi>of the ſame Month, that his R. H. was very ſenſible of his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty's Friendſhip, and that he would labour to cultivate it with all the good Offices he was capable of doing his Majeſty,</hi> [the French King]; <hi>that he was fully convinced their Intereſts were both one; that my Lord</hi> Arlington <hi>and the Parliament were not only unuſeful, but very dangerous both to</hi> England <hi>and</hi> France; <hi>that therefore it was neceſſary they ſhould do all they could to diſſolve it. I did communicate this Deſign of mine to Monſieur</hi> Ravigni, <hi>who agreed with me, that it would be the greateſt Advantage imaginable to his Maſter, to have the D's Power and Credit ſo far advanced.</hi> — IF WE CAN ADVANCE THE DUKE'S INTEREST ONE STEP FORWARD, WE SHALL PUT HIM OUT OF THE REACH OF CHANCE FOR EVER:—<hi>Then would Catholicks be at reſt, and his moſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Majeſty's Intereſt ſecured with us in</hi> England, [mark that] <hi>beyond all Apprehenſions whatſoever.</hi>—<hi>Our prevaling in theſe things would give the greateſt Blow to the</hi> PROTESTANT RELIGION <hi>here, that ever it received from its Birth</hi>—.</p>
            <p>— <hi>If the Duke ſhould once get above them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">☞</note> 
               <hi>(after the Tricks they have play'd with him) they are not ſure he will totally forget the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage he has had at their Hands</hi>—.</p>
            <p>—<hi>We have</hi> (proceeds <hi>Coleman</hi>) <hi>here a</hi> MIGHTY WORK <hi>upon our Hands, no leſs than</hi> THE CONVERSION <hi>of three Kingdoms, and by that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the utter ſubduing of a</hi> PESTILENT HERESY, <hi>which hath domineered over great part of the Northern World a long time. There were never ſuch Hopes of Succeſs ſince the Death of our Queen</hi> Mary, <hi>as now in our Days, when God has given us a Prince who is become (may I ſay to a Miracle) zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of being the Author and Inſtrument of ſo glorious a Work.</hi>
               <note place="margin">☞</note> —<hi>That which we rely upon moſt, next to God Almighty's Providence, and the Favour of my Maſter the Duke, is</hi> THE MIGHTY MIND <hi>of his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty.—I muſt confeſs, I think his Chriſtian Majeſty's</hi> TEMPORAL IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEREST <hi>is ſo much attracted to that of his R. H. (which can never be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable but upon the Growth and Advancement of the</hi> CATHOLICK RELIGION) <hi>that his Miniſters cannot give him better Advice,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now Gentlemen; might not a Man have concluded, that what you then read, and find here repeated, ought to have weaned your Party, at leaſt ſuch of you as pretended to be of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> (for I well remember you ſcoffed at the Name of <hi>Proteſtant</hi>) from your ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101573:4"/>
               <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor?</hi> What I could no King pleaſe ſuch Churchmen as you, but ſuch <hi>AZEALOT as would not regard any thing in the World, in compariſon of overturning our Religion?</hi> Could no one content you, but a Prince, whoſe <hi>Intereſt was</hi> avowed to be <hi>inſeparably united to that of the Grand Tyrant of the Earth?</hi> Who declared himſelf fully convinc'd that <hi>PARLIAMENTS were not only <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>N<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SEF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L, but very DANGE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S to the JOINT INTEREST both of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> France? None but <hi>him by whom the French King's Intereſt was to be ſecured in</hi> England? None but him <hi>who undertook to give the greateſt Blow to the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion here, that it ever received from its Birth?</hi> None but him, who <hi>ſhould he once get above us (after the Tricks we had then plaid him)</hi> [by the way he remembers we have plaid him a worſe ſince] <hi>WO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LD NOT TO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TALLY FORGET the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage he has had at our Hands?</hi> Finally, could nothing pleaſe you but a King, whoſe MIGHTY WORK (as you were forewarned) <hi>was to be no leſs than the Deſtruction of the Nations,</hi> under the Notion of <hi>converting</hi> them, and who was <hi>utterly to ſubdue our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as a</hi> PESTILENT HERESY? One, of whom our inhumane Enemies promiſed themſelves <hi>greater Hopes than ever they had ſince the Death of cruel Queen</hi> Mary? A Prince whom they boaſted was become (to <hi>a Miracle</hi>) <hi>zealous of being the Author and Inſtrument of ſo glorious a Work,</hi> as that of razing the Foundations of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Could I now believe that I diſcourſe to rational Creatures, and not to Brutes void of all Underſtanding, I ſhould hope to make you bluſh at your paſt Frenzies, if not perſwade you to ceaſe doting on your old Bondage, and hankering after the <hi>Fleſh-Pots</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> to give over your <hi>Murmuring,</hi> and no longer to foment Jealouſies between the King and his People, no longer to be throwing in Sparks of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, and endeavouring to blow them up into Flames of Mutinies and Rebellions. Allow me to remember you (in the Words of a loyal and learned Perſon) that <hi>God has given our King a People, who, tho they may ſometimes be practiſed upon to run into <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>proars, yet Loyalty is ſo inlaid in their Tempers, and annealed to their Souls, that the ſecret Enemies of our King and Peace could never yet make their Earnings out of them; nay, that God has converted our Danger into our Security, that he has made the People, not the Terror of the Government, but of its Enemies: That ſome ill Men have an ill and envious Eye upon the Throne, but they fear the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> Mr. <hi>Alſop</hi>'s Thankſgiving-Sermon at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> 8 <hi>Sept.</hi> 1695.</p>
            <p>Run not then I caution you headlong to Deſtruction, but be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed to conſider what you are doing; why will you be helping for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward your Countries Ruine, by labouring to ſubject it to that <hi>mighty Nimrod,</hi> the ſecuring whoſe <hi>Intereſt</hi> in <hi>England</hi> was the wicked Deſign
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101573:4"/>ſo long ſince on foot? 'Tis evident to all the World, that you, under the Name of TORIES (in which you gloried) brought Church and State to the very Door of Deſtruction, gave us the diſmal: Proſpect of Slavery in our Perſons, Conſciences and Eſtates; and by your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement we beheld every thing that was dear and valuable to us up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Brink of Subjection to a foreign Power: and all by pleading for and adhering to your darling <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor.</hi> Nay 'tis beyond Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction clear, that you were blinded, deluded and beguiled, in that Point, by the ſubtile Jeſuits, thoſe Firebrands of all <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſeeing it has pleaſed God to bleſs us with the grateful <hi>Surprize</hi> of a Deliverance from ſuch great Evils, will you be perſwaded to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a loyal quiet People, diſpoſed to Obedience? To inforce this up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, as 'tis your Intereſt as well as Duty, I ſhall recount to you, what was in vain laid before you when you firſt ran <hi>a madding</hi> after <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery</hi> and <hi>Slavery.</hi> A ſincere Lover of his Country then argued with you to this Effect:</p>
            <p>You were then truly told, that <hi>thoſe who were for the Duke of</hi> York<hi>'s Intereſt were moſt certainly for theſe three Intereſts,</hi> viz. 1. For the <hi>Popiſh Intereſt.</hi> 2. For the <hi>French Intereſt.</hi> 3. For <hi>Tyranny</hi> or <hi>Arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> term it as you will; and by Conſequence againſt theſe other three things. 1. <hi>Againſt the Intereſt of the Church of</hi> England, and the <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi> 2. Againſt <hi>the Intereſt of</hi> England, your native Country. 3. Againſt <hi>the Intereſt of Parliaments,</hi> and ſo againſt your own Freedoms as you were <hi>Engliſhmen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You were then exhorted ſeriouſly to conſider theſe things, your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, your Lives, your Liberties, your Eſtates, your All being deeply concerned therein.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You were rightly admoniſhed, that <hi>if you ſtood for the Duke's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, you did undoubtedly ſo far ſtand for that of the Pope;</hi> and would thereby give the greateſt Blow to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> it ever had ſince it was a Church.</p>
            <p>The Matter was thus expoſtulated with you; <hi>Can you once imagine that by bringing in a Popiſh Succeſſor, you will not inevitably ſet up Popery?</hi> Will ſuch a King, think you, have ſo great a Love for another Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion as his own, or for thoſe of another Profeſſion, (whom he eſteems <hi>Hereticks</hi>) as for thoſe of his own? Nay then, will it not naturally follow, that he will advance the one, and diſcountenance and depreſs the other? Will it not be the only way to get into Office or Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to turn <hi>Papiſt?</hi> What will the Effect of this be, in a little time, think you? Will it not be a great weakning to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> to have her Members allured and ſeduced from her, and turn'd and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101573:5"/>kept out of Places of Truſt, Profit and Honour, whilſt her Enemies are placed in them? Conſider further, whether in endeavouring to make a <hi>Papiſt</hi> Head of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> you do not labour to make her <hi>a Monſter;</hi> for if <hi>our Head</hi> reckon <hi>us his Body</hi> rotten <hi>Hereticks,</hi> where's our Body? Where will our Church be? What Agreement between the Head and the Body? Will it not inevitably run into Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion? <hi>Shall we have a Father of our Church, who by his own Faith ſtands obliged to deſtroy her,</hi> and is bound by the Romiſh Principles to deal with her as a Harlot? Conſider now, are you willing to ſend your ſelves, Wives, Children, Fathers and Mothers, to be burnt at the Stake for <hi>Hereticks?</hi> Will you yet perſiſt to endeavour to put your Religion once more into the Hazard of a wicked <hi>Queen</hi> Mary<hi>'s Perſecution?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>In being for the Succeſſion of the D. of</hi> York, <hi>you are undoubtedly for the French Intereſt,</hi> and ſo conſequently againſt the Intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> your native Country. That he did ever eſpouſe that Tyrant's Intereſt, is evidently diſcovered, and by a Copy of a Letter which was taken amongſt his Secretary <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Papers, will be yet further evinced, tho indeed it was not made out that it was drawn by the <hi>Duke's</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, nor could it be expected that <hi>Coleman</hi> ſhould accuſe his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> who flatter'd him to the laſt Moment of his Life with the vain Hope of a <hi>Pardon.</hi> That Letter was entituled; <hi>The Copy of the Letter to Monſieur</hi> Le Cheſe, <hi>the French King's Confeſſor,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> confeſſed he himſelf wrote, and counterfeited in the Duke's Name; it runs to this Effect:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>The 2d of <hi>June</hi> laſt paſt, his <hi>moſt Chriſtian Majeſty</hi> offered me moſt generouſly his Friendſhip, and <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of his Purſe to the Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance againſt the Deſigns of</hi> MY ENEMIES AND HIS; and proteſted unto me, that <hi>his Intereſt and mine were ſo clearly link'd together,</hi> that thoſe that oppoſed the one ſhould be look'd upon as <hi>Enemies</hi> to the other; <hi>and told me</hi> moreover HIS OPINION of my Lord <hi>Arlington</hi> and the PARLIAMENT; which is, that <hi>he is of opinion, that neither the one nor the other is in his Intereſt or mine.</hi>—I was much ſatisfied to ſee his <hi>moſt Chriſtian Majeſty</hi> altogether of <hi>my Opinion;</hi> ſo I made him an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the 29th of <hi>June,</hi> by the ſame Means he made uſe of to write to me, that is, by <hi>Coleman,</hi>—and entirely agreed to his <hi>moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Majeſty,</hi> as well to what had reſpect to <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of our Intereſts,</hi> as THE UNUSEFULNESS of my Lord <hi>Arlington</hi> and THE PARLIAMENT, in order to the Service of the <hi>King my Brother,</hi> and his <hi>moſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Majeſty,</hi> and that it was neceſſary to make uſe of our <hi>joint and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most Credits,</hi> to prevent the Succeſs of thoſe <hi>evil Deſigns</hi> reſolved on by the Lord <hi>Arlington</hi> and <hi>the Parliament, against his most Chriſtian
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101573:5"/>Majeſty and my ſelf;</hi> which of my ſide I promiſed really to perform: <hi>Of which ſince that time I have given reaſonable good Proof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Moreover, I made ſome Propoſals, which I thought neceſſary to bring to paſs what we were obliged to undertake, aſſuring him that <hi>nothing could ſo firmly eſtabliſh</hi> OUR INTEREST <hi>with the King my Brother, as that very ſame Offer of the Help of</hi> HIS PURSE, by which means I had much Reaſon to hope I ſhould be enabled to perſwade to <hi>the diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Parliament,</hi> and to make void <hi>the Deſigns</hi> of my Lord <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lington,</hi> who works inceſſantly to advance <hi>the Interest of the</hi> PRINCE OF ORANGE and the <hi>Hollanders, and to leſſen that of the King your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</hi> — Seeing that my Lord <hi>Arlington,</hi> and ſeveral others, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by a thouſand Deceits to break <hi>the good Intelligence which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the King my Brother, his most Chriſtian Majeſty, and my ſelf,</hi> to the end they might deceive us all three, <note place="margin">☞</note> I have thought fit to adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe you of all that is paſt, and deſire of you your Aſſiſtance and Friendſhip, to prevent THE ROGUERIES of thoſe who have no other Deſign than <hi>to betray the Concerns of</hi> France <hi>and</hi> England <hi>alſo</hi>—.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Review this, I intreat you, and deny it if you can, that <hi>theſe Kings were early of one Piece.</hi> The <hi>French King</hi> wrote himſelf to the <hi>Duke,</hi> yet we are to believe it if we will, that <hi>Coleman counterfeited this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,</hi> and <hi>his Royal Highneſs</hi> had not the good Breeding to acknowledg the Receipt of the Letter of ſo generous a <hi>Confederate,</hi> who offered <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of his Purſe against the Deſigns of</hi> THEIR ENEMIES. We here find <hi>the Enemies</hi> of the one declared <hi>Enemies of the other,</hi> and <hi>the Parliament in the Interest of neither.</hi> Their <hi>joint and utmost Credits</hi> are to be made uſe of to prevent the Succeſs of the WICKED DESIGNS of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> againſt the French King and the Duke [which was to exclude them both;] the one by the Help of the others Purſe, is to be enabled to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade to <hi>the diſſolving the Parliament,</hi> and to make void <hi>the Deſigns to advance</hi> THE INTEREST OF THE PRINCE OF ORANGE and the HOLLANDERS, and to leſſen that of the <hi>French King</hi> [which Deſigns were only an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Purpoſe to ſet Bounds to that impetuous Torrent, which then highly threatned to overwhelm this Part of the World]. To remark no further, <hi>the French Aid is here craved to prevent</hi> THE ROGUISH DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIGNS <hi>of an Engliſh Parliament against the then</hi> LEAGUE WITH FRANCE.<note place="margin">☞</note> To proceed now to the third Head, from which we have digreſſed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It was urged upon you, that <hi>if you were for a Popiſh King, then by Conſequence you were for Arbitrary Government, and against Parliaments.</hi> Is it not notoriouſly known, that the Duke bears an implacable Hatred
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101573:6"/>to <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and that none more than he ever ſet himſelf againſt them? <hi>If then he ſhould ſucceed his Brother,</hi> [or as the Caſe at preſent ſtands, ſhould ever return] <hi>adieu to Parliaments:</hi> You are then at beſt to expect <hi>French Slavery;</hi> and were you to enjoy it alone, I am almoſt provok'd to wiſh you were now in the poſſeſſion of it.</p>
            <p>You were thus told <hi>what would be the Manner of the King that you would have reign over you,</hi> and what reaſon you would find to cry out in that day <hi>becauſe of your King.</hi> Now inſtead of following the Text, and ſaying, <hi>the Lord will not hear you in that day;</hi> I do here obſerve, that all the good People of theſe Nations are laid under the higheſt Obligations to praiſe the Almighty for having heard <hi>their Cry,</hi> in the day of their Diſtreſs <hi>becauſe of your King;</hi> and to give us ſuch <hi>a Prince</hi> as we groaned for, ſuch <hi>a Prince</hi> as we wanted, ſuch <hi>a Prince</hi> whoſe Intereſt leads him to eſpouſe the Cauſe and Intereſt of the Land, which he ſaw to be viſibly betrayed; and which <hi>our Enemies</hi> would at once have raviſhed from us, had not Providence over-ruled them.</p>
            <p>Finding now that I have inſenſibly launch'd out into this wide Ocean of <hi>the Popiſh Plot,</hi> I ſhall take leave to diſcourſe a little further upon that Subject, purpoſing to preſent my Reader with a conciſe Abridgment of the Hiſtory of that tranſcendent Villany; and ſhall in this place very briefly touch ſome Points relating to it, and to the firſt Diſcoverer; becauſe my old Friends the <hi>Tories</hi> did, and do im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently deny the Thing, or at leaſt extenuate it, and falſly ſuggeſt that very few were concern'd in it; that it was nothing ſo bad as the World took it to be, and that, notwithſtanding the Votes of divers Parliaments that there was a Plot to murder the King, alter the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and ſubvert the Eſtabliſhed Religion.</p>
            <p>I have met with Inſinuations, which at firſt view ſeem plauſible, they will have Dr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s <hi>Information</hi> to be <hi>Fictitious;</hi> alledging that it is improbable he ſhould come in ſo ſhort a time to a diſtinct know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of ſo many Particulars; or if he had heard or ſeen them, that he ſhould remember them; and that if he went among them, with an intent to diſcover them, why did he not do it ſooner? Theſe, when well weighed, will, I am ſatisfied, be found very frivolous.</p>
            <p>When he was firſt admitted among the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> they made him <hi>a Meſſenger</hi> for their Society; which exactly fell in with his Deſign to detect their Villanies: They ſent him with Letters into <hi>Spain;</hi> thoſe he opened, and thereby began to ſmell ſomething of their Helliſh De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns. After this he was taken into their <hi>Conſult,</hi> and ſo had the liberty to ſee and hear what was then acting, and to enquire how paſt <hi>Intrigues</hi> had been carried on. Thus he came to underſtand that <hi>the City of</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101573:6"/>London <hi>was fired by the Jeſuits,</hi> how that Plot was laid, and who were the Actors in it.</p>
            <p>He kept ſhort Notes of all things that occurred from the time he was admitted into their Society, with intent to produce them when they might be of uſe, which enabled him to give ſo exact an Account of all Occurrences: Theſe were confirm'd by other Circumſtances, and collateral Evidence; ſo that <hi>in ſome hundreds of Particulars no one thing has interfer'd with another, nor with thoſe Papers which have been found elſewhere,</hi> or with thoſe Informations which have been given in by others. For inſtance; <hi>He informs that</hi> Coleman <hi>was a principal Agent in this Conſpiracy, Letters found inform the ſame: He informs that he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered Commiſſions received from</hi> Langhorne, <hi>Letters intercepted make mention of Commiſſions ſent, which they hope were delivered.</hi> In ſhort, it was impoſſible that a Man ſhould contrive ſuch a Thing, attended with ſo many hundreds of Circumſtances, and comparing them with ſo many Papers, Informations, and Examinations of ſo many other Men, but they would interfere with one another if falſe; therefore, it may juſtly be concluded the whole is true, till ſomething be found to the contrary: and then it follows, that here was a moſt bloody, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villiſh, and helliſh Deſign, which hath been in ſome meaſure carrying on to this day.</p>
            <p>I muſt here take the liberty to digreſs a little, and lay before you what Obſervation the Lord-Chief-Juſtice <hi>Scroggs</hi> made upon Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> his Evidence of this <hi>Plot,</hi> as you may read in the Trial of <hi>Ireland, Pickering,</hi> and <hi>Grove,</hi> (<hi>pag.</hi> 72.) When the <hi>Matter</hi> (ſays he) <hi>is ſo accompanied with ſo many other Circumſtances,</hi>
               <note place="margin">☞</note> 
               <hi>which are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Things, and cannot be evaded or denied, it is almoſt impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for any Man to make ſuch a Story, or not to believe it after it is told. I know not whether they can frame ſuch a one, I am ſure never a Proteſtant ever did, and I believe never would invent ſuch a one to take away their Lives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as to <hi>the time of this Diſcovery;</hi> if on the firſt Intimation of the Deſign he had made a Diſcovery of it, it is more than probable he had been rejected, becauſe he could not make out the Particulars as at length he did, and yet found no ſmall difficulty to be received. Further; He was not at his own Command when he was engaged in their Society; had he moved any way without, or contrary to their Order, he had preſently been ſuſpected, and might eaſily have been detected. But being ſent from St. <hi>Omers</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> he laid hold of that Opportunity, and ſhewed his real Intention to preſerve the <hi>King's Life,</hi> and his <hi>Native Countrey</hi> from this accurſed <hi>Conſpiracy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:101573:7"/>
            <p>Will you pleaſe now to allow me to lay before you the Opinion of the ſaid Lord-Chief-Juſtice <hi>Scoggs</hi> as to this Ridiculed Plot, as he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered it in the before-mentioned Trial of <hi>Ireland, Pickering</hi> and <hi>Grove:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>moſt plain the Plot is diſcovered, and that by theſe Men; and that it is a Plot, and a Villanous one, nothing is plainer:</hi> No Man of common Underſtanding but muſt ſee <hi>there was a Conſpiracy to bring in Popery, and to deſtroy the Proteſtant Religion;</hi> and we know their Doctrines and Practices too well to believe they will ſtick at any thing that may effect theſe Ends: They muſt excuſe me if I be plain with them; I would not aſperſe a Profeſſion of Men as the Prieſts are, with hard words, if they were not very true, and if at this time it were not very neceſſary. <hi>If they had not murdered Kings, I would not ſay they would have murdered ours;</hi> but when it has been their Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice ſo to do, when they have debauched Mens Underſtandings, overturned all Morals, and deſtroyed all Divinity, what ſhall I ſay of them? When their Humility is ſuch that they tread upon the Necks of Emperors, their Charity ſuch as for to kill Princes, and their Vow of Poverty ſuch as to covet Kingdoms, what ſhall I judg of them? When they have Licence to Lie, and Indulgences for Falſhoods; nay, when they can make him a Saint that dies in one, and then pray to him, (as the Carpenter firſt makes an Image and afterwards worſhips it) and then can think to bring in that Wooden Religion of theirs amongſt us in this Nation; What ſhall I think of them? What ſhall I ſay of them? What ſhall I do with them?—</p>
               <p>— I have ſaid ſo much the more in this Matter, becauſe their Action are ſo very plain and open, and yet ſo pernicious; and <hi>it's a very great Providence that we and out Religion are delivered from Blood and Oppreſſion.</hi> I believe our Religion would have ſtood notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Attempts; and I would have them to know we are not afraid of them; nay, I think we ſhould have maintained it by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying of them. We ſhould have been all in Blood it's true; but the greateſt Effuſion would have been on their Side; and without it, how did they hope it ſhould have been done? —</p>
               <p>I return now to the <hi>the Fact which is proved by two Witneſſes, and by the concurrent Evidence of the Letter and the Maid;</hi> and the Matter is as plain and notorious as can be, that <hi>there was an Intention of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Popery by a Cruel and Bloody Way:</hi> — I leave it therefore to you to conſider, whether you have not as much Evidence from theſe two Men as can be expected in a Caſe of this Nature, <note place="margin">☞</note> and <hi>whether Mr.</hi> Oates <hi>be not rather juſtified by the Teſtimony offered againſt him
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101573:7"/>than diſcredited.</hi> Let Prudence and Conſcience direct your Verdict, and you will be too hard for their Art and Cunning.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Now I am to obſerve to you, that the Jury having brought in theſe Criminals guilty of the Treaſon for which they ſtood indicted, the ſame Lord-Chief-Juſtice, whom Bleſſed Memory promoted, did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs himſelf in theſe words: <q>You have done Gentlemen like very good Subjects and very good Chriſtians; that is to ſay, like very good <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and now much good may their <hi>thirty thouſand Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> do them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Hear now the Opinion of your old and moſt endeared Friend <hi>Jef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fries</hi> to this Point, at the time when he, as Recorder of <hi>London,</hi> paſs'd Sentence of Death upon <hi>Langhorne</hi> and the five Jeſuits; his words were theſe:</p>
            <p>— Nor is there the leaſt room for the moſt ſcrupulous Man to doubt of the Credibility of the Witneſſes, that have been examined againſt you: And ſure I am, you have been fully heard, and ſtand fairly convicted of thoſe Crimes you have been indicted for.</p>
            <p>Hearken once more, and underſtand what the ſame Recorder <hi>Jef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feries</hi> declared upon the Jury's giving their Verdict upon the five Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits; it was this:</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon a long Evidence, a full diſcuſſing the Objections made againſt it, and a patient hearing of the Defence they made, they are found Guilty: And I do think that every Honeſt Man will ſay, that they are unexceptionably found ſo; and that 'tis a juſt Verdict you have given.</p>
            <p>Bear with me now before I conclude, that I am your Remembrancer, that in hope of ſtifling this Plot, the Bloody Conſpirators barbarouſly murdered a Worthy Magiſtrate Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey;</hi> who upon the 27th of <hi>Sept.</hi> 1678. took Dr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Information upon Oath, and theſe inhumane Villains allowed him not to ſurvive it above 14 days; and I ſhall lay before you <hi>Scroggs</hi>'s Declaration concerning it, as made in the Trial of the five Jeſuits.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>While this Gentleman's Blood</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>lies upon you, it muſt be yet further</hi> told you, that in what you did do, you have given a Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of what you would do: We have a Teſtimony that for promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting your Cauſe you would not ſtick at the Blood of Proteſtants; you began with Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey,</hi> but who knows where you would have made an end? It was this one Man you killed in his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but in Effigie the whole Nation. It was in one Man's Blood your Hands are embrewed, but your Souls were dipt in the Blood of us all; this was a Handſel only of what was to follow: and <hi>ſo long as we are convinced you killed him, we cannot but believe you would alſo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101573:8"/>have killed the King:</hi> We cannot but believe you would make all of us away that ſtand in the way of your Religion. A Religion, which, according to what it is, you would bring in upon us by a Converſion of us with Blood, and by a Baptiſm with Fire: God keep our Land from the one, and our City from the other.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To return; (ſays <hi>Scroggs</hi>) <q>
                  <note place="margin">☞</note> 
                  <hi>The Letter that is found in</hi> Harcourt<hi>'s Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers does further confirm Mr.</hi> Oates <hi>in all the great and conſiderable Matters that he ſays;</hi> that there was a Plot, that that Plot was called by the name of a Deſign, which was to be kept cloſe and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret; and <hi>this is an Evidence that cannot lie.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But after all, I know you of <hi>the Jacobite Party</hi> will upbraid me, that notwithſtanding ſuch ſtrong Confirmation of all that the Doctor had witneſſed, and that by Evidence which could not lie, it is well known he was afterwards convicted of <hi>Perjury:</hi> So he was, and I care not if I digreſs a little to remind you of the manner of doing it.</p>
            <p>As an Introduction to it the virulent Pen of that Man of effronted Impudence, <hi>L'Eſtrange</hi> I mean, is employed to vilify nor only the Evidence, but Parliaments; nay, the Proteſtant Religion it ſelf: <hi>Addreſſes of Thanks</hi> for the Violation of our Rights, in the Diſſolution of Parliaments, were made and moſt graciouſly received, the Preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of them being uſually honoured with Knighthood, and rewarded with Preferment to Places of Truſt and Profit. I have the Name of one of you at my Tongue's end, but at this time for his Brother's ſake I'll ſpare him.</p>
            <p>By theſe and ſuch like Arts, it became the common Cry of a profli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Party in every Corner of <hi>England, Popery is better than Presbytery;</hi> at leaſt the Papiſts and Diſſenters are equally dangerous, if not all one: 'Tis therefore more than time that a <hi>Colledge</hi> be hang'd againſt a <hi>Pickering.</hi> The Nation was almoſt put beſides it ſelf, by the doleful Cry of <hi>Blood, Blood, Aſſociations, Conſpiracies, Rebellion, Treaſon,</hi> and what not, that was frightful and terrible.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf could not poſſibly have ordered Matters better for the Service of Holy Church: <hi>The Proteſtant Religion is now mock'd, Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments derided, the Witneſſes of the Plot vilified, and the Belief of any other than a Presbyterian Plot vaniſhes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Proceeding gave new Life and Heart to the Popiſh Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and ſtruck no ſmall damp upon their Proſecutors. Of the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes ſome were bought off, and others terrified from their Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: But Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> being no way ſhaken, but bearing with undaunted Courage and Conſtancy, innumerable Reproaches and Slanders from the Pulpit and Preſs, nay and from the Stage alſo; Hell it ſelf ſeemed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101573:8"/>to be engaged to diſcredit, and batter down the Belief of his Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. <hi>Knox</hi> and <hi>Lane,</hi> to blaſt his Reputation, were imployed to accuſe him of an unuſual but moſt heinous Wickedneſs; that Plot not obtaining, and Matters being prepared for placing unmasked Popery upon the Throne, he was condemned in 100000 <hi>l.</hi> for affirming the Duke of <hi>York</hi> to be a Papiſt, and thereupon ſecured againſt the deſired Seaſon for the Conſpirators taking their full Revenge upon him.</p>
            <p>The Way being thus prepared for the execution of their Deſign upon him, on the 8th of <hi>May</hi> 1685. he was brought to Trial in the Court of <hi>King's Bench,</hi> upon an Indictment for evidencing <hi>that there was a treaſonable Conſult at the White-horſe-Tavern in the</hi> Strand <hi>the</hi> 24th <hi>of</hi> April, 1678. <hi>at which</hi> Whitebread, Fenwick <hi>and</hi> Ireland <hi>were preſent; and that they there came to a Reſolution to murder the King, and that the Defendant carried the Reſolution from Chamber to Chamber, to be ſigned by the Jeſuits; whereas in Truth he was not preſent, nor carried any ſuch Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to be ſigned, and ſo committed wilful Perjury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall here lay down a ſummary Account of the Proceedings in this Trial; and if the Reader be curious to have farther Information therein, I refer him to a more ample Relation thereof in the Tract called <hi>A Diſplay of Tyranny,</hi> (the firſt Part) printed in 1689.</p>
            <list>
               <head>The Names of the Judges then in Court were,</head>
               <item>Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Jefferies,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. Juſtice <hi>Wythens,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. Juſtice <hi>Holloway,</hi> and</item>
               <item>Mr. Juſtice <hi>Walcot.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The Fame of the firſt will be ever remembred. The ſecond was advanced to a Seat upon the Bench for promoting and preſenting an Addreſs, expreſſing <hi>an Abhorrence</hi> to petition for the Calling and Sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Parliaments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Holloway</hi> had been very inſtrumental in the Murder of brave <hi>Stephen Colledge,</hi> which entitled him to this Promotion. And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Walcot</hi> was a mean Wretch, and by conſequence a fit Tool to ſerve the Purpoſes of that Juncture.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <head>The Names of the Jury pack'd upon him were,</head>
                  <item>Sir <hi>William Dodſon,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Edmond Wiſeman,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard Aley,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Fowle,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Blackmore,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Peter Pickering,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert Bedingfield,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Rawlinſon,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Roger Reeves,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ambroſe Iſted,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henry Collyer,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard Howard.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Every Man then of your own Gang, I aſſure you.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:101573:9"/>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <head>The King's Counſel were,</head>
                  <item>Attorney General <hi>Sawyer,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Solicitor General <hi>Finch,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Recorder of <hi>London,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>North,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Jones,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Hanſes.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt of whom was, Sir <hi>Roger,</hi> your <hi>Aſſiſtant</hi> in your malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Scriblings, and your Brother-Burgeſs in K. <hi>James</hi>'s Parliament for <hi>Wincheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They produced for Witneſſes about 20 <hi>Jeſuits and Students</hi> of St. <hi>Omers,</hi> who all teſtified that the Defendant came to St. <hi>Omers</hi> in <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> 1677. and went not from thence until <hi>June,</hi> 1678.</p>
            <p>I ſhall here obſerve how theſe Jeſuited Sparks were careſſed and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, both by the Court and Counſel. Their Evidence was received without the leaſt Interruption, not one croſs, thwarting, or doubting Queſtion being put to any one of them: Nay, there was not found ſo much Temper as to permit the Defendant to propoſe his Queſtions to them; which made him with undaunted Courage cry out, That his Defence was under a very great Prejudice, and that there was <hi>a Turn</hi> to be ſerved, and therefore he was not admitted to ask the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes Queſtions; and ſaid, I do verily believe, that <hi>at this rate, it is more ſafe for Papiſts to be Traitors, than for any Proteſtant to diſcover a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Plot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeems alſo worth the noting, that to inſinuate that <hi>Oates</hi>'s Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence was not always true and credited, the King's Counſel produced the Earl of <hi>Caſtlemain</hi> and Sir <hi>George Wakeman, who declared that what he ſwore against them at their Trials was falſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here <hi>Jeffries</hi> obſerving the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s Undauntedneſs, ſaid, I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſee any one that has the Face of a Man, carry it at this rate, <hi>when he hears ſuch Evidence brought against him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which the <hi>Doctor</hi> replied, I wonder Mr. <hi>Attorney</hi> will offer to bring this Evidence: <hi>Jeffries</hi> (whoſe Character with K. <hi>Charles</hi> the Second was, that <hi>he had the Impudence of ten Carted Whores</hi>) in a raving Fit retorted, Such Impudence was never ſeen in any Chriſtian Nation, you are a Shame to Mankind! To which the <hi>Doctor's</hi> Reply was, No my Lord, I am neither a Shame to my ſelf, nor to Mankind: <hi>What I have ſworn is true, and I will ſeal it with my Blood, if occaſion be: Ah, Ah, my Lord, I know why all this is, and ſo may the World; but</hi> THIS WILL NOT DO THE WORK, <hi>to make the Plot to be disbelieved; things are not to be done by great Noiſes, I will ſtand by the Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:101573:9"/>
            <p>He obſerved in his Defence, that the <hi>Indictment</hi> againſt him <hi>was ſix Years after the pretended Perjury;</hi> That moſt of the Witneſſes who now gave Evidence againſt him, were thoſe who were brought to confront him at the Trial of the five Jeſuits; and tho there were ſome freſh Witneſſes, the Evidence of all of them was the ſame as then, but their Teſtimony rejected, as it was at <hi>Langborne</hi>'s Trial; and that the Jury upon convicting the Jeſuits were told by the Court, that <hi>their Verdict was unexceptionable;</hi> and this by <hi>Jeffries</hi> himſelf. And,</p>
            <p>Then he produced four or five Witneſſes who clearly proved his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>London</hi> as he had ſworn, at the time of the <hi>White-horſe-Conſult,</hi> in <hi>April,</hi> 1678.</p>
            <p>After this he offered Objections to the Validity of the Evidence againſt him: As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>a Papiſt, in a Cauſe of Religion, is not to be received and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved as a good Witneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here <hi>Wythens</hi> interpoſed, ſaying, <hi>Is not a Papist as good a Witneſs as a Diſſenter?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which was anſwered by citing <hi>Bulſtrode</hi>'s Reports, Part 2. 155. <hi>A Popiſh Recuſant is not to be admitted a Witneſs between Party and Party:</hi> which was alſo my Lord <hi>Coke</hi>'s Opinion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wythens</hi> replied, <hi>May a Presbyterian be a good Witneſs, Mr.</hi> Oates? And <hi>Holloway</hi> (who had aſſiſted the Blood-hounds to murder <hi>Colledge</hi>) ſaid, Or <hi>would</hi> Colledge <hi>have been a good Witneſs, Mr.</hi> Oates?</p>
            <p>Moſt certainly by the Rules of Law, the Teſtimonies of theſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ought not to have been offered in this Caſe, to delude the People; and the Civil Law ſo fully concurs with our Common Law in rejecting Enemies to be Witneſſes, in the Cauſe of their Enemy, that <hi>it denies Credit to what they may teſtify in the Cauſe of their Enemy, with their dying Breath, after they have received the Eucharist.</hi> This is the general Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the Doctors of the Civil Law: <hi>Inimicus, etiamſi in Articulo Mortis conſtitutus, &amp; accipiſſet Euchariſtiam, repellitur à Teſtimonio Cauſa ſui Inimici.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He then urged the Judgments of Papiſts in Caſe of Conſcience, whereby <hi>they maintain the vilest Wickedneſs to be lawful for the Church's Service.</hi> And they acknowledg, <hi>they have Diſpenſations to ſwear Lies for promoting the Catholick Cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:101573:10"/>
            <p>Then he concluded to this effect: <q>My Lord, this I ſay, <hi>The Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for which I am indicted is the ſame which I delivered ſix Years ago,</hi> where there were 16 Witneſſes againſt me, but what Credit did they receive? <hi>I do avow the Truth of the Popiſh Plot, and will ſtand to it whilst I live:</hi> Was ever Man dealt with as I am, or had ſuch Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence offered againſt him? My Lord, this I am ſure of, <hi>if I had been a Witneſs against thoſe who ſuffered in the late Fanatick Plot</hi> (as 'twas called) <hi>I had never been called in queſtion, if my Evidence had been falſe:</hi> but 'tis apparent <hi>the Papiſts have now a Turn to ſerve,</hi> and theſe St. <hi>Omers</hi> Youths are brought to falſify my Evidence, and to bring off the Lords who ſtand impeached of High Treaſon for the <hi>Popiſh Conſpiracy.</hi> My Lord, 'tis not me they indict, but the whole <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Interest</hi> is aimed at in this Proſecution: For my own part I care not what becomes of me, <hi>the Truth will one time or another appear.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the Day following, (<hi>May</hi> 9. 1685.) the <hi>Doctor</hi> was tried up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an Indictment for another <hi>ſuppoſed Perjury;</hi> but that Proſecution be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Complection with what is here preſented, I trouble not the Reader with it farther than to lay before him the Names of the Jury.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Sir <hi>Thomas Vernon,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nicholas Charleton,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Langham,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Hartop,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Francis Griffith,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Kent,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>George Toriano,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Henry Loades,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Midgley,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Pelling,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Short,</hi> and</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>George Peck.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>All Men of the ſame Kidney ſtill.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Juries having, according as directed by that <hi>Man of Blood Jeff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> brought the <hi>Doctor</hi> in guilty of both the Perjuries, comes <hi>the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrer of Parliaments,</hi> the tender-hearted, good natur'd Proteſtant Judg <hi>Wythens,</hi> to pronounce the Sentence; previous to it he tells the Defendant, that no Chriſtian's Heart can think of the <hi>Innocent Blood</hi> which was ſhed by his Oath, without bleeding: That every knowing Man believed, and every honeſt Man grieved for it. He proceeds, <hi>God be thanked, our Eyes are now open.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Judgment, beſides Impriſonment, Fine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was, that on <hi>Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday</hi> next <hi>he be whipt from</hi> Aldgate <hi>to</hi> Newgate, <hi>and upon Friday from</hi> Newgate <hi>to</hi> Tyburn.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:101573:10"/>
            <p>This (ſays <hi>Wythens</hi>) I pronounce to be the Judgment of the Court upon you; and I muſt tell you plainly, <hi>If it had been in my Power to have carried it farther, I ſhould not have been unwilling to have given Judgment of Death upon you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This cruel Sentence was executed with all the Circumſtances of Barbarity; ſo that tho (which <hi>Wythens</hi> lamented) the Law did not allow them to condemn him directly to Death, they might well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that the Execution of this Sentence would have deſtroyed him, as in all Probability it had, if a very honeſt and able Chyrurgion, Mr. <hi>James Waſs,</hi> had not (with the Hazard of his own Life) under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken the Cure of him, and under God preſerved him; I ſay he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried that Cure through with the Hazard of his Life, and that <hi>gratis,</hi> tho he was wholly a Stranger to the Doctor; for there was another skilful Chyrurgion, and very honeſt Man, Mr. <hi>Charles Bateman,</hi> who had promiſed to undertake it, but at that very Inſtant was clapp'd into <hi>Newgate,</hi> and ſoon after murdered.</p>
            <p>He ſuffered ſome thouſands of Stripes, to his unſpeakable Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and was ten Weeks under Mr. <hi>Waſs</hi>'s Hands. Their Malice and Cruelty did not ceaſe here, but becauſe (through the Mercy of God ſupporting him, and the extraordinary Care and Skill of his judicious Chyrurgion) he was like to outlive that barbarous Uſage, ſome of them, whilſt he was weak in Bed, got into his Chamber, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to pull off the Plaiſters from his Back, threatning to deſtroy him. And,</p>
            <p>That nothing might be wanting to compleat his Miſery and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, they procured him to be loaded with Irons of exceſſive Weight for a whole Year without Intermiſſion, and that when his Legs were ſwollen with the Gout; and to be ſhut up in the Hole or Dungeon of the Priſon, whereby he became impaired in his Limbs, and contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Convulſion-Fits, to the Hazard of his Life.</p>
            <p>To conclude now, ſee here the Senſe of the Houſe of Commons upon this wicked Proſecution, and curſed Sentence, as it appears by the following Vote.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:101573:11"/>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="Parliamentary_resolution">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Martis,</hi> 11th <hi>Junii,</hi> 1689.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Reſolved, That the Proſecution of <hi>Titus Oates,</hi> upon two Indictments for Perjury, in the Court of <hi>King's-Bench,</hi> was <hi>a Deſign to ſtifle the Popiſh Plot,</hi> and that <hi>the Verdicts</hi> given thereupon <hi>were corrupt,</hi> and that <hi>the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> given thereupon were <hi>cruel</hi> and <hi>illegal.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:101573:11"/>
            <head>A Brief ABSTRACT of Dr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Narrative of the POPISH PLOT, as it was made upon Oath on the <hi>27th</hi> of <hi>September, 1678,</hi> before Sir <hi>Edmund-Bury Godfrey,</hi> one of the Juſtices of the Peace for the County of <hi>Middleſex;</hi> and before the King and Council on the <hi>28th,</hi> and <hi>29th</hi> of the ſame Month; and after publiſh'd by Order of the Right Honourable the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled, in <hi>April 1679.</hi> With Remarks thereupon.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Kind Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THO I accoſt you in this familiar Way, and uſe a friendly Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation, here's no Plot upon you; no not ſo much as a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to draw you in to read this Pamphlet. Nay ſhould I perceive you ſo much as ſtart at the very Title, I ſhould eſteem you yet more kind if you throw it away; for if you read on, and are then found to ſnarl at me, we may have the ill Luck to ſall together by the Ears, and it ever was my Choice to live in a whole Skin.</p>
            <p>That I may ſo do, I give you not the advantage of ſaying I was the firſt Aggreſſor. I do not, I will not commend the <hi>Thing:</hi> No, I will not ſo much as recommend it to your Peruſal; I will not ſo much as tell you what is in it: No, I will not ſo far gratify you as to declare
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101573:12"/>why I do emit it, further than to ſay that 'tis my Will and Pleaſure ſo to do. And,</p>
            <p>Now, if not invited, not encouraged, you will read on, 'tis at your Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril; if upon thoſe Terms you dare adventure further, you muſt know that the following Narrative was uſhered into the World, under an Addreſs to K. <hi>Charles</hi> the II. to the Effect following, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Great Sir!</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>This Narrative of the preſent <hi>Horrid Plot</hi> againſt our Majeſty and Government, which was firſt heard and narrowly diſcuſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your ſacred Majeſty and Council, and afterwards by both Houſes of Parliament, with univerſal Aſſent to the Power of Truth herein, is at laſt to appear abroad for the Satisfaction of theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and <hi>Europe</hi> perhaps, touching the Myſtery and Conſequence of ſuch Deſigns. —</p>
                  <p>—How little the Criminals concerned in this Plot deſerve from your Majeſty, the World will better judg, if they will but conſider how graciouſly your Majeſty has dealt with them and <hi>connived</hi> at them, while the Rigour of the Law was let looſe upon your other <hi>diſſenting Subjects,</hi> who yet continued more quiet and loyal under their Preſſures and Provocations, than theſe under Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and Careſſes. Hath not your Majeſty hazarded the Hearts and Affections of your beſt Subjects, and much of Royal Honour in appearing for the late Indulgence with Fruſtation, to win and oblige, if poſſible, theſe <hi>Everlaſting Holy Cut-throats?</hi> —How can your Majeſty expect Truth and Sincerity, where Treaſons and Lies are Vertues and Merits? —</p>
                  <p>—I queſtion not, <hi>Great Sir,</hi> but that he in whoſe hands are the Hearts of <hi>Princes,</hi> will in time fully convince your Majeſty of all their unworthy Principles and Practices, and of my <hi>Integrity</hi> too, how ſtrange ſoever ſome open or ſecret Papiſts, whom time alſo may diſcover, have endeavoured to repreſent me. Till that time I commit my Cauſe to the moſt Righteous and All-ſeeing Judg, with <hi>a Reſolution to perſevere through his Aſſiſtance in my Truth and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, againſt all Diſcouragements or Terrors,</hi> or <hi>Blandiſhments either, to the laſt Gaſp.</hi> —</p>
                  <p>—I cannot forbear to pray to God out of my Sincerity and Zeal for publick Peace and Concord between King and People: That ſeeing your Majeſty muſt highly truſt ſome or other for your neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Eaſe and Help, that God would put it into your Majeſty's Heart
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101573:12"/>more to truſt and rely upon your two Houſes of <hi>Parliament</hi> (who will be moſt true to your Laws, and conſequently both to you and your People) than to any <hi>ſingle Miniſter</hi> or <hi>Miniſters</hi> whatſoever, unaccountably; who may pretend to more Loyalty, or more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with any <hi>Humour,</hi> or humane Frailty of your Majeſty's, but are not true Friends to your Majeſty, or their Country, or themſelves therein; but erect and prefer an Imperial, <hi>Paramount</hi> Self-end or Luſt before all; which your Majeſty by their Art muſt be brought unworthily to ſerve and promote, to publick Diſturbance always, and the Confuſion of themſelves and their Poſterity, moſt an end by God's juſt Vengance.</p>
                  <p>It is a falſe Suggeſtion which ſome Tempters uſe, that a King that rules by Will is more great, or glorious, or ſtrong, than a King that rules by Law: The Quality of the Retinue beſt proves the State of the Lord; the one being but a King of Slaves, while the other, like God, is a King of Kings and Hearts. <hi>No Prince was ever more abſolute to have what he wiſhed, than Queen</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>who wiſhed for nothing more than her Subjects Rights and Welfare.</hi> —</p>
                  <p>—Nothing will make your Majeſty ſo amiable and acceptable in the Eyes of God and Man, and your Name and Memory bleſſed and glorious for ever, as the Copying of the Laws of our Saviour in your Life, by a decent Paternal Example before the Sons and Daughters of your People; to increaſe the Fear of God and its Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences amongſt us: It being the chief End and Work of all Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Powers to ſuppreſs Vice and encourage Vertue; which is beſt done abroad, when firſt and effectually begun at home in your own Houſe and Family; by baniſhing all vicious Livers from your Preſence and Converſe, and advancing the Vertuous in their ſtead: By the neglect of which principal Part of their Royal Truſt and Office, Princes depoſe themſelves as uſeleſs before God and their own Conſciences, whatever may be their State or Glory in Fact; and by humane Laws and Power before Men.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Our Royal Patron being thus diſmiſs'd, we are now got to the Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative it ſelf: of which you (my kind Reader ſtill) may, or may not, as you chooſe, run over the Heads. They are theſe,</p>
            <p>The general Deſign in this Plot was <hi>the Reformation,</hi> that is in their Senſe, the Reduction of <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> by the Sword, to the <hi>Romiſh Religion</hi> and Obedience. And,</p>
            <p>—Beſides <hi>the Papal,</hi> there was alſo a <hi>French Plot</hi> carried on by Sir <hi>Ellis Leighton,</hi> Mr. <hi>COLEMAN</hi> and others.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:101573:13"/>
            <p>— <hi>The King's Perſon</hi> they more eſpecially reſolved to remove, and that with all poſſible ſpeed, <hi>by Dagger, Piſtol or POISON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—<hi>The Prince of Orange</hi> is <hi>to be cut off;</hi> — He was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned againſt and condemned by Name; and 12 <hi>Miſſioners</hi> ſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Holland,</hi> had it in charge to put that People in Mutiny againſt him.</p>
            <p>—On the 4th of <hi>January, (ſtilo novo)</hi> Letters were ſent by <hi>Richard Aſhby</hi> and others, Jeſuits of the Engliſh Seminary at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> to the Father Confeſſor of the Emperor, to adviſe him that his Majeſty of Great <hi>Britain</hi> had treacherouſly plotted the Ruine of the Confederates, — and that his Deſign was not to keep any Alliance with his Imperial Majeſty, but only in ſhew, that he might advance his Nephew <hi>THE PRINCE OF ORANGE,</hi> and make him abſolute; and therefore prayed <hi>that the States of</hi> Holland <hi>might be acquainted with it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Letters arrived at <hi>London,</hi> bearing Date <hi>Aug.</hi> 5. 1678, from <hi>Whito,</hi> alias <hi>Whitebread</hi> Provincional, to <hi>John Fenvick,</hi> from St. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers;</hi> in which he did inform the Fathers that he had ordered 12 Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits to go for <hi>Holland,</hi> and to inform the Dutch that <hi>the Prince of</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range <hi>did intend to aſſume the Crown of a King,</hi> and that he reſolved to bring them under another Government; which was deſigned to beget in the Dutch an evil Opinion of the P. of <hi>Orange,</hi> and to procure a Commotion there againſt him.</p>
            <p>On the 11th of <hi>Aug. John Keines,</hi> a Jeſuit, declared that all means were now uſed to beget a difference between the Dutch and the P. of <hi>Orange;</hi> and if that could be effected, there was no queſtion to be made, but that the Proteſtant Intereſt would fail in <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the 12th of <hi>Aug.</hi> a Pacquet arrived in <hi>London,</hi> from <hi>White,</hi> alias <hi>Whitebread,</hi> the Provincional, and other Jeſuits, to <hi>John Fenwick,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating that the twelve Jeſuits were got into <hi>Holland,</hi> and would uſe all their Skill and Intereſt to make a Commotion there; and that <hi>APPLE-TREE WILL.</hi> (meaning the P. of <hi>Orange</hi>) <hi>SHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LD NOT BE GREAT.</hi> And that they hoped the Fathers in <hi>London</hi> would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their Buſineſs cloſely there.</p>
            <p>In order to the Reduction of <hi>Ireland</hi> it was reſolved, that the D. of <hi>Ormond</hi> muſt be put out of the way, and that then the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants ſhould be cut off, as in 41; and to that end Arms and Money were ſent over, and the Pope contributed 800 Thouſand Crowns: and to make all ſure, the French were to ſend Forces over to join 25 thouſand Iriſh.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:101573:13"/>
            <p>On the 11th of <hi>Aug. John Keines</hi> the Jeſuit declared, that the Provincional had taken great care of keeping alive the Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the diſaffected Scots and D. <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> and that the Affairs in <hi>Ireland</hi> went on with great Expedition, and that <hi>fourty eight</hi> would not laſt long in <hi>England,</hi> for it was high time to hinder <hi>fourty nine</hi> from being effected. That <hi>Barly-broth</hi> ſhould grow dead, and <hi>Twelve</hi> would be cut off, and that: <hi>Mum</hi> and <hi>Chocolate</hi> ſhould be put down, and <hi>the Order of Magpyes</hi> ſhould be turned into their Primitive Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Habit; now the Deponent ſaith that the Words (<hi>hinder</hi> 49 <hi>from being effected</hi>) is an Expreſſion that is uſed amongſt them, for <hi>cutting off the King,</hi> that he may not live to be compleat forty nine Years of Age: and by <hi>Barley-broth</hi> is meant the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> which ſhall be turned out and ſit no more: and by <hi>Mum</hi> and <hi>Chocolate</hi> is meant <hi>the Proteſtant Peers,</hi> who, if not deſtroyed, ſhall never have any Vote in the Houſe of Peers more after the Death of this King; and by <hi>Magpyes</hi> they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand <hi>the Biſhops,</hi> whoſe Habit in Parliament is <hi>Black and white,</hi> which ſhall be changed into <hi>Purple;</hi> and by <hi>Twelve</hi> is meant <hi>the Duke of Monmouth.—Keines</hi> on the 12th of <hi>Auguſt</hi> determined to go for <hi>Windſor</hi> in order to ſettle ſome Buſineſs there, towards the diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 48—and told the Deponent that <hi>he might chance to fall ſhort of his return again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>July</hi> 1678. <hi>Richard Strange</hi> (the laſt Provincial of the Jeſuits) did encourage the Deponent to go on in aſſiſting the Society in carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on <hi>the Deſign;</hi> and told the Deponent that <hi>they got</hi> 14000 l. <hi>in the Fire of</hi> London <hi>in</hi> 1666. The Deponent ask'd <hi>Strange</hi> how they came to effect that <hi>great and famous Buſineſs?</hi> He replyed, that himſelf and <hi>Gray, Pennington</hi> and <hi>Barton,</hi> Jeſuits, with ſome others, together with <hi>Keimaſh,</hi> a Dominican Fryar, join'd with one <hi>GREEN,</hi> and met at one <hi>Weſt</hi>'s Houſe, the Green Dragon at <hi>Puddle Dock,</hi> and there debated about the manner of firing the City, and where they ſhould begin, and <hi>did attempt it in</hi> February, 1664/5.—In <hi>January</hi> 1665/6, they met with this <hi>Green</hi> again, who cloſed in with them in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; and that they might ingratiate themſelves with <hi>Green,</hi> they Man, and fit for their Purpoſe. And the more to engage him, <hi>they pretended to bold many of the Fifth-Monarchy Principles;</hi> which when <hi>Green</hi> perceived, judging them to be real, he brought them acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with eight others, who were zealous in the Buſineſs. The Jeſuits were earneſt to have it done in <hi>February,</hi> but <hi>Green</hi> prayed them to ſuſpend that Reſolution, becauſe the King would not be much in Town, if at all, till the Plague was more abated; who, <hi>Green</hi> did ſay
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101573:14"/>muſt be cut off too, when the People were in a hurry by reaſon of the Fire; and <hi>this Motion well pleaſed the Jeſuits and Dominican,</hi> and ſo it was put off. That in a very little time after, <hi>Green</hi> and the reſt of thoſe <hi>Fifth-Monarchy-Men,</hi> together with the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Dominican,</hi> were ſuſpected by <hi>Weſt,</hi> and forewarned his Houſe. And preſently after Green <hi>and his eight Acquaintance were clapt up in Priſon;</hi> and upon their Impriſonment <hi>the Jeſuits and Dominican got away to St.</hi> Omers, and there remained till the <hi>May</hi> after the Execution of 8 of theſe Perſons, <hi>Green</hi> dying in <hi>Newgate.</hi> —That in the beginning of <hi>June,</hi> being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>London,</hi> they began afreſh to conſult about this <hi>Fire,</hi> (which was ſtill carried on by the Society in their abſence) and they determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to cut off the King in the time of the Fire, that <hi>the Number of the Beaſt might be accompliſhed.</hi> At the uttering of which words, <hi>Strange</hi> broke out into a great Laughter: But ſaid <hi>Strange,</hi> to be ſhort, <hi>we got</hi> 50 <hi>or</hi> 60 <hi>Iriſh to ply the Work.</hi> — We were alſo in fee with ſeveral <hi>Frenchmen,</hi> who were faithful in the Buſineſs. — <hi>Strange</hi> told the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent that they ſpent 700 Fire-Balls; and <hi>when the Fire-Merchants were at work, then others were employed to plunder what they could.</hi> —</p>
            <p>They have communicated what Secrets they can have reveal'd to them of the King, which they ſend over to <hi>Le Cheſe, the French King's Confeſſor:</hi> —This they do by one <hi>Smith,</hi> who daily lurks about <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi> and in Parliament-time about <hi>Weſtminſter-hall</hi> and the <hi>Lobby.</hi> —And <hi>One</hi> COLEMAN, <hi>formerly Secretary to her Royal Highneſs, doth aſſiſt this</hi> Smith <hi>with private Intelligence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the 10th. of. <hi>Auguſt</hi> the Deponent did meet with <hi>Groves,</hi> who had promiſed to give him an Account of <hi>the Fire of Southwark</hi> in 1676: and then told him that he had certain Fireworks made for that purpoſe; and he, with three <hi>Iriſhmen</hi> his Aſſiſtants, went to St. <hi>Margaret</hi>'s-<hi>Hill,</hi> where they found an <hi>Oil-Shop,</hi> which <hi>Groves</hi> bragg'd he fir'd. — He ſaid that Dr. <hi>Fogarthy</hi> procured the <hi>Iriſhmen,</hi> for which the Society (<hi>Richard Strange</hi> then Provincial) gave them 1000 <hi>l. viz.</hi> 400. <hi>l.</hi> to <hi>Groves,</hi> and 200 <hi>l.</hi> apiece to the three <hi>Iriſhmen,</hi> and that <hi>the Society got at leaſt</hi> 2000 <hi>l. by that Fire:</hi> which was alſo told the Deponent at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time by <hi>Richard Strange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the 11th of <hi>Auguſt</hi> the Deponent ſaw Letters from St. <hi>Omers,</hi> written by Father <hi>IRELAND</hi> to <hi>John Fenwick;</hi> — and <hi>Fenwick</hi> told the Deponent that <hi>if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> lived till Chriſtmaſs, he ſhould ſee a good Change of Things;</hi> either that <hi>Forty eight</hi> [the King] <hi>ſhould be taken from the World, or the World</hi> (eſpecially the little he was concern'd in) <hi>ſhould be taken from him:</hi> And <hi>ONE THAT WAS A CATHOLICK SHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LD PLAY S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CH A GAME, AS NEVER WAS PLAY'D SINCE THE
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101573:14"/>CONQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EST;</hi> and <hi>Fenwick</hi> told the Deponent, <hi>that this Catholick was the D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>KE OF</hi> YORK. —</p>
            <p>This Plot was to be effected by theſe Means (amongſt others); — <hi>By diſcloſing the King's Counſels to</hi> France, <hi>by</hi> Coleman, Smith, <hi>and others:</hi> — <hi>By diſaffecting his Majeſty's Allies,</hi> Holland, Spain, <hi>the</hi> German Emperor <hi>and</hi> Princes; <hi>by falſe Intelligence,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>By diſturbing Trade. — By firing and plundering our beſt Cities and Towns: — By horrid,</hi> worſe than <hi>Jewiſh Intereſt; Tranſportation of Trade, People, Stock, and Money; AD<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LTERATING MONEY AND PLATE. To which end they have Bankers, Brokers, Merchants, Goldſmiths and other Traders, whom they ſtock and ſet up with Money of their Society; of which they boaſt to have</hi> 100 <hi>thouſand Pounds Caſh,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I deſcend now to ſum up the whole, and deſcant a little upon ſome few of the Heads before recounted.</p>
            <p>Great Britain <hi>and</hi> Ireland <hi>were to be reduced by the Sword to the Romiſh Religion and Obedience:</hi> In order hereunto, <hi>the King</hi> was to be removed by <hi>Dagger, Piſtol,</hi> or <hi>Poiſon;</hi> and they declared 'twas high time it were effected.</p>
            <p>And good reaſon for it: He had broke his Word with <hi>Madam</hi> his Siſter, in paſſing the Teſt-Bill; having promiſed her at the Interview at <hi>Dover,</hi> that nothing ſhould be done to the prejudice of the R. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks: And contrary to his Promiſe to the Papiſts, they remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred his ſending the Great E. of <hi>Eſſex</hi> into <hi>Ireland.</hi> They well knew alſo that he had refuſed to ſign <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Declaration for diſſolving the Parliament, (which he had ſworn to them to do) and that he had been guilty of that never-to-be-forgiven Sin againſt their Church, of receiving the Sacrament in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and that the ſame day at Noon on which he had received it in the Morning from <hi>Ireland</hi> the Jeſuit: To add no more, they knew that they had at hand a more daring Prince, who they were aſſured would ſtake his Crown for car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on their <hi>Mighty Work.</hi> The <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> they had reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>ſhould by no means become Great,</hi> therefore he muſt be cut off; and in order to effect that <hi>mighty,</hi> and ſo highly neceſſary <hi>Work,</hi> Miſſioners are ſent into <hi>Holland</hi> to ſtir up that People to mutiny againſt him, upon the wicked Suggeſtion that he <hi>reſolved to change their Government, and aſſume a Crown.</hi> The <hi>Emperor</hi> is inſtigated to create a Belief in the <hi>States General</hi> that that <hi>Prince</hi> deſigned to make himſelf Abſolute; and they promiſe themſelves, that by a Breach between the Prince and States, the <hi>Proteſtant Intereſt</hi> would without queſtion fail in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:101573:15"/>
            <p>Now to reflect a little upon this Matter; Why muſt this Prince be cut off? Was he not the Duke of <hi>York</hi>'s Siſter's Son? 'tis yielded: What then can we expect that that ſhould avail him? No ſurely; for we ſee his Uncle was converted to ſuch a degree of Zeal, as not to regard any thing in the World in compariſon of the Converſion of Heretical Kingdoms; ſo his Intereſts we find were ſo inſeparably uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to that of the French King, that it was impoſſible to divide them. We are told, that by all means the Moſt Chriſtian King's Intereſt in <hi>England</hi> muſt be ſecured; and that for a weighty Reaſon, <hi>viz. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his and the D. of</hi> York<hi>'s prevailing, would give the greateſt Blow to the Proteſtant Religion here, that ever it received from its Birth.</hi> Then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who at that time ſtood within a ſtep or two of the Throne, ought in all Policy to be removed.</p>
            <p>You cannot forget that they had <hi>a mighty Work</hi> upon their hands, the Converſion of three Kingdoms, and Subduing <hi>the Peſtilent Northern Hereſy.</hi> They never had ſuch hopes of Succeſs as at that time, ſince the Death of their Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> The Duke was to a Miracle zealous of being the <hi>Author</hi> and <hi>Inſtrument</hi> of ſo Glorious a Work; and they told us they relied upon him, and the <hi>mighty Mind</hi> of the moſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an King; and further, his Temporal Intereſt was acknowledged to be highly attracted to that of the Duke.</p>
            <p>'Tis evident they had <hi>mighty Work, mighty Hopes, and mighty Minds,</hi> employed about it. Is it to be admired then that they reſolved to paſs <hi>a Bill of Excluſion</hi> upon our Prince, who, as all the World knew, ſtood ready with all his Might to baffle theſe <hi>mighty <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay further, as the French King's Intereſt was attracted to that of the Duke's, ſo was the Prince's to that of <hi>England, Holland,</hi> and the Reformed Churches of <hi>Europe;</hi> or in their words, to the Support of that <hi>Northern Hereſy</hi> which theſe <hi>mighty Nimrods</hi> were to ſubdue. What ſignifies a Nephew in ſuch a Caſe as this?</p>
            <p>But ſtop a little I pray, and take another Reaſon: His moſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Majeſty did moſt generouſly offer the Duke <hi>the uſe of his Purſe</hi> to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt againſt the Deſigns of both <hi>their Enemies;</hi> nay, he proteſted that thoſe that oppoſed the one, ſhould be look'd upon as Enemies to the other; and withal declared his Opinion, that <hi>the Parliament of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>was not in either of their Intereſts,</hi> and the Duke did entirely agree to it, and that they were unuſeful to both: ſo that (in his poor Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) it was neceſſary to make uſe of <hi>both their joint and utmost Credits,</hi> to prevent the Succeſs of the Parliament's <hi>Evil Deſigns</hi> againſt them both, which of his ſide <hi>he promiſed really to perform.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:101573:15"/>
            <p>Nay, which is more, do not you remember the Duke tells the French King of a very dangerous Plot againſt <hi>them both? My Lord</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lington <hi>was inceſſantly at work to advance the Intereſt of the Prince of</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range <hi>and the Hollanders, and to leſſen that of the French King;</hi> and that he and ſeveral others were endeavouring to break the good Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence between K. <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, the French King, and the Duke; wherefore his Royal Highneſs earneſtly ſollicites the moſt Chriſtian King to aſſiſt with <hi>the help of his Purſe</hi> to prevent ſuch <hi>RO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERIES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee here is <hi>a Triple League</hi> againſt a <hi>Triple Confederacy;</hi> The King of <hi>England,</hi> French King, and Duke of <hi>York,</hi> againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England,</hi> the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> and his Royal Highneſs the Pr. of <hi>Orange:</hi> The French is to furniſh the Sinews of War, Money: <hi>The Parliament are declared Enemies;</hi> K. <hi>Charles</hi> indeed ſtanding only as a Cypher, the French King and the Duke put themſelves under the moſt ſolemn Engagements to perform what was ſtipulated, and ſtrenuouſly to aſſiſt <hi>each other</hi> againſt the Deſigns of <hi>both their Enemies;</hi> and ſeeing there was <hi>a deſperate Deſign to advance the Prince,</hi> and to leſſen the French, the Duke puts in his Memorial to that King, deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his Aſſiſtance to prevent ſuch <hi>Rogueries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return to our Narrative; <hi>The Houſe of Commons is no more to ſit:</hi> No, nor was it adviſable they ſhould; they were proclaimed E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to <hi>France,</hi> and to the Duke. The French King (whoſe Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt was to be ſecured in <hi>England</hi>) was fully convinced that they were not only unuſeful, but very dangerous to both their joint Intereſts, [may they ever continue ſo;] and it much ſatisfied the Duke, to ſee his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty altogether of his Opinion in the Point: Then with what reaſon could we expect the uſe of Parliaments would be continued? The <hi>Proteſtant Peers</hi> as to be deſtroyed, or excluded the Houſe; and the <hi>Magpy</hi> are to be changed for Purple <hi>Biſhops.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And who at this day has the effronted Forehead to ſay, that all this was Fiction? Did not they embrew their Hands in the Blood of ſome of our Nobility? And were not more threatned to that degree, that 8. Years ſince no true Proteſtant Lord in <hi>England</hi> could at any rate have got his Head or his Seat in Parliament enſured to him for one Year? Such was the Caſe of our <hi>Biſhops:</hi> We beheld ſome of their Dioceſſes viſited by thoſe of the <hi>Purple Dye;</hi> and had not Heaven in a miraculous way delivered them, we might not at this day have ſeen a <hi>Black and White One</hi> in the Nation.</p>
            <p>In order to the Accompliſhment of their ſanctified Villanies, the Jeſuits, with the Aſſiſtance of French and Iriſh Papiſts, burnt <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:101573:16"/>and <hi>Southwark;</hi> and that they might the more ſecurely carry on that Deſign without being detected, they cunningly draw in a few ſilly Fifth-Monarchy-Men, and fairly leave them in the lurch, to be hang'd, as they were about <hi>April</hi> 1666.</p>
            <p>When any Popiſh Plot is near the Point of Execution, they ever will have the Diſſenters at hand to account for their Villanies. The burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Neſt of Hereticks had been concerted both at <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Paris,</hi> and the time for putting it in execution approaching, in <hi>April</hi> 1666, a Fanatick Plot is brought upon the Stage, and ſeven or eight were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned at the <hi>Old-Baily, for plotting to kill the King, and to burn the City on the</hi> 3d <hi>Day of</hi> September <hi>following,</hi> (the very Day the Papiſts after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards did it.) For a more full Account of this, I refer the Reader to the <hi>London-Gazette</hi> of <hi>April</hi> 30, 1666. <hi>Numb.</hi> 48.</p>
            <p>Thus when they were cock-ſure of cutting off K. <hi>Charles</hi> the Second before <hi>Chriſtmaſs,</hi> 1678. Mr. <hi>Claypole</hi> (Son-in-Law to <hi>Oliver</hi>) was made cloſe Priſoner in the <hi>Tower,</hi> in <hi>July,</hi> 1678. upon an Accuſation of <hi>conſpiring the Death of the King;</hi> and it is very probable, that had not Dr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Diſcovery happily interpoſed, he might have died for it the next Term, and the King been ſoon ſent after him.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>our Counſels are to be betrayed to</hi> France: that Part is committed to Mr. <hi>Coleman, the Duke or Dutcheſs of</hi> York<hi>'s Secretary;</hi> and he is to manage it by a Correſpondence with <hi>Le Cheſe, Confeſſor to the French King.</hi> [I cannot with-hold my ſelf, from remarking here, that this Information was given upon Oath on the 27th of <hi>September,</hi> 1678. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sir <hi>Edmond-Bury Godfrey,</hi> and before the King and Council the 28th and 29th of that Month; that hereupon <hi>Coleman</hi> was taken up on the 29th, and his Papers ſeized, which happily furniſhed the World with irrefragable Evidence (had there been no other) of that diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Intrigue].</p>
            <p>In fine, <hi>Trade is to be diſcouraged</hi> [that ſo it was, I know none will deny:] <hi>Our Coin was to be adulterated</hi> [I ſhall not ſurely be called upon to prove that that was done to purpoſe]: and to crown the day, King <hi>Charles</hi> was not to be reprieved beyond <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> 1678. and then our <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor</hi> was to play us ſuch a <hi>Game</hi> as never was plaid ſince the Conqueſt.</p>
            <p>[They miſtook the time indeed, but the Feat was done, and then the Gameſter came upon the Stage to play his Game; but having an unlucky Hand, he quickly plaid himſelf out, and therefore I ſhall not further purſue him; I only ſay to him, as the Welſhman did to his Horſe, There's a Trick for your Trick, and a Stone in your Foot ſtill.]</p>
            <p>Proceed we now to the further Narrative of this helliſh Conſpiracy, of which it ſeems requiſite to hint theſe things.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:101573:16"/>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi> after he had endured a long and moſt cruel Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, upon a Judgment for 100000 <hi>l.</hi> Damages given againſt him to the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> for ſaying the Duke was a Papiſt; now ſaw that his irreconcilable Enemy upon the Throne, and that he with his Jeſuits and corrupt Judges were reſolved to run upon him with all their Rage, as they did in <hi>Eaſter-Term,</hi> 1685. ordering him to be tried in the Court of <hi>King's-Bench</hi> upon two ſeveral Indictments, for two pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Perjuries, in his Evidence concerning the Plot, and that upon the Teſtimony of thoſe very Popiſh Witneſſes who had confronted him in three ſeveral Trials of the Conſpirators.</p>
            <p>The Caſe ſtanding thus with him, and remembring that his Life had been ſeveral times attempted, was now under an Apprehenſion that they were bent upon his Deſtruction, and therefore in the Month of <hi>April,</hi> 1685. he drew up this enſuing Narrative in the Preſence of Sir <hi>Robert Thomas</hi> Baronet, <hi>John Arnold,</hi> and <hi>John Dutton-Colt</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſqs</abbr> and having ſigned it with his own Hand, depoſited it with a Perſon of Worth and Quality, with whom I am well aſſured it has ever ſince remained, till upon the 21st of <hi>January</hi> 1695/6. it was put into my Hands.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="narrative">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:101573:17"/>
            <head>Dr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s further NARRATIVE of the Popiſh Plot, <hi>29 April, 1685.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Malice of my Popiſh Adverſaries being ſo great, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but judg that they deſign nothing leſs than my Ruine, in Revenge for that Service I did my Country, in diſcovering their more than abominable and helliſh Conſpiracy againſt the Life of the late King, the Proteſtant Religion, and the Government, as by Law eſtabliſhed, both in Church and State; I thought it my Duty, in caſe of any harder Uſage than I have yet met with, to put ſomething in Writing, which my Friends I hope will publiſh for the Satisfaction of my dear Country-men, for whoſe Cauſe I have been a living Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, expoſed to the Rage and Reproach of a Generation of Men, who neither fear God, nor reverence Man; whoſe Religion is either the worſt of Religions, or their Morals ſo debauched, that they are fit to be of any Religion except that of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Therefore in the firſt place, I do declare my ſelf to be a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as by Law eſtabliſhed, both in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Diſcipline; yet I muſt confeſs ſhe ſtands in need of a further Reformation; and it would be happy if that by the Removal of ſome Ceremonies uſeleſs and dangerous, a way might be made for a more perfect Union amongſt all Engliſh Proteſtants, that our Hands might be ſtrengthned againſt the Common Enemy the Papiſts, in order to the rooting out of Superſtition and Idolatry from amongſt us, that we may avert thoſe Judgments from this Nation, that do ſo highly threaten our total Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>It hath been the greateſt Grief of my Heart, to ſee Proteſtants contending one with another about the meaner Parts of Religion and Worſhip, whilſt the Enemy, the Popiſh Party, ſtands by and adds Fuel to our Flames, and nouriſhes the Quarrel, till we have expoſed our ſelves to be devoured by them, and have wounded thoſe amongſt us who are weak in the Faith. I could likewiſe wiſh, that our diſſenting Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren would lay aſide their Scruples in ſome things, and comply with
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:101573:17"/>their Brethren in thoſe Ceremonies that are innocent and harmleſs, and not inconſiſtent with the Word of God, and the Law of our great Lord Jeſus Chriſt; and that they that can conform, for Chriſt's ſake, do not perſecute their Brethren, who through Tenderneſs of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience cannot partake with them in thoſe Advantages that ſome of them have enjoyed to their Hearts Content.</p>
            <p>Truly I have been ſo far from being inclined to perſecute any for Conſcience ſake, that I would not have had the leaſt Thought of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving or adviſing the Proſecution of Popery, or moleſting of any that are in Communion with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but that the Religion of <hi>Rome</hi> is a Conſpiracy againſt God and Chriſt, and Mankind; for ſhew me a Papiſt that is thorow-paced, I will ſhew you a Murderer of the People of God, a Firer of Cities, a declared Enemy to the Peace and Tranquillity of the Sons of Men. Now Men that are ſo united toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt God and all Goodneſs, our Religion, Lives and Liberties, muſt be rooted out, and not ſuffered to continue amongſt a well go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned People: for they make it their Buſineſs to debauch our looſer ſort of Chriſtians, and reproach and calumniate thoſe whoſe Firmneſs to their God and the Goſpel of Chriſt renders them Men above their Temptations, tho by their Allurements ſome have been ſeduced to their Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Therefore as for the Popiſh Religion, I do declare that I do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and abhor it, as a Religion whoſe whole Foundation is Blood, Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, Murder and Rapine; a Religion that ſtands in oppoſition to the Rule and Law of Jeſus Chriſt. And the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> whom they call <hi>Pope,</hi> I believe to be Antichriſt that exalts himſelf in the Temple of God above God, and all that is called God, the Son of Perdition and everlaſting Wrath.</p>
            <p>But that which is expected of me is, that I do declare my ſelf fully concerning the damnable Plot carried on by the Popiſh Party for the Deſtruction of the late King and the Proteſtant Religion: I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Acquaintance I had with ſome conſiderable Papiſts in the Year 1670. made me to ſuſpect a Deſign carrying on by them to advance their own Religion, and to pull down ours; but I little thought that they had a Deſign of murdering the King, which in proceſs of time I found out.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:101573:18"/>
            <p>There was one <hi>Cotton</hi> that was at Mr. <hi>Guilfourd</hi>'s in <hi>Kent,</hi> that was often very pleaſingly tempting me to come over to their Church; for, ſaith he it will not be long before you muſt either burn or turn, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore come over in time, that your coming over may be looked upon as meritorious. This <hi>Cotton</hi> ſince I underſtood to be a Prieſt of the Society of Jeſus, and one that was ingaged in the Popiſh Plot; and with him I had a better and more intimate Acquaintance: From him at firſt I found that the Popiſh Party had a Deſign of promoting their Religion, and making what Proſelytes they could in order to the inlarging their Intereſt and Power in this poor Nation; I from that time had a great Deſire to get into them, to ſee whither their Deſigns tended, being very fearful that they deſigned no leſs than the Ruine of our Religion and Government. Nay, this <hi>Cotton</hi> had the Impudence to tell me, that the King was engaged with them to advance their Cauſe and Religion, and was reſolved to bring in Popery, it being a Religion that was moſt conſiſtent with Monarchy, and that his Majeſty was reſolved to be like his Neighbour-Princes: this was in the Year 1670, about <hi>Chriſtmaſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Diſcourſe I did diſcover to Mr. <hi>Walter Drury,</hi> whom I did aſſiſt in the Service of his Cure at <hi>Sandburst</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent;</hi> and he told me, that that Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> had talked as badly, or rather worſe to him, but he had ſufficiently told him his own, ſo that <hi>Cotton</hi> was ſhy of having any farther Diſcourſe with h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> about thoſe Matters; and withal Mr. <hi>Drury</hi> having threatned to complain of him, Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> did withdraw from that Family, and another came in his room.</p>
            <p>In the Year 1672, I was acquainted with one <hi>Keimaſh,</hi> who was very perſwaſive in his Arguments to have brought me over to their Church; he then frequented <hi>Arundell</hi>-houſe in the <hi>Strand,</hi> and was a Fellow that had inſinuated himſelf into the Acquaintance of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Divines of our Church, and bragged that he had recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled above thirty Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> but I found him a debauched lewd Fellow, and ſo my Acquaintance ceaſed with him; for it was a hard Matter, unleſs in a Morning, to find him ſober. I found him afterwards to have been Chaplain to the old Counteſs of <hi>Arundell,</hi> with whom he lived ſeveral Years, under the Notion of her Steward.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:101573:18"/>
            <p>In the Year 1672, I left Mr. <hi>Drury</hi>'s Cure, and held a Living of my own, which I reſided upon for ſome time, called <hi>Bobbing</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> and from thence I went and ſerved his Majeſty at Sea as a Chaplain, where I found many Difficulties by reaſon of Sickneſs of Body. I refreſhed my ſelf at <hi>Tangire:</hi> There was one <hi>Gerard</hi> an Iriſh Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nican, that upon the firſt ſight of me, required of me, <hi>Whether the Catholick Religion was eſtabliſhed in</hi> England? (this was in the Year 1674. in the Month of <hi>April</hi>) and I told him No: Why then, ſaid he, <hi>the Dutch War is to no purpoſe:</hi> Why, ſaid I, was our engaging in a War againſt the Dutch to bring in Popery? Well, well, ſaith the Friar, you will ſee in time. In ſome few Days we had notice of a Peace with the Dutch: What then, ſaid he, <hi>our great King of</hi> France <hi>is not at Peace with them, and he muſt do the Work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Year 1675, I had obtained an Intereſt with <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> then Earl of <hi>Norwich,</hi> and Earl Marſhal of <hi>England,</hi> who was very kind to me upon the Account of my contending earneſtly for his Right of Preſenting to a Living in the Dioceſs of <hi>Chiche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> to which Living the then Biſhop (a turbulent Man) pretended a Right of Collating: And in the Year 1676, I was made his Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain; and I call the whole Family of the <hi>Norfolk Howards</hi> to witneſs to my Fidelity to him and to his Children, tho I am but churliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed by ſome of them for my Truth and Fidelity to my Lord and Maſter; but God forgive them for their Ingratitude to me, eſpecially <hi>Charles Howard,</hi> who owes me more than I ſhall mention here; but I always had a Thought that Popery rendred a Man incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of being grateful to his Friend.</p>
            <p>I, in the Service of the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> came acquainted with ſeveral Prieſts; and being then reſolved upon a ſtrict Inquiry into their Deſigns againſt us and our Religion, and Laws and Liberties, I met with one <hi>Berry</hi> a Prieſt, that had been a Jeſuit, but had left that Order through ſome Diſcontent and Madneſs that had ſeized the poor Wretch, as he hath told me. He was a Scholar in <hi>Cambridg,</hi> was a Miniſter in <hi>England,</hi> if he told me the Truth, then turned Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit, and then (as before) left that Order and became a ſecular Prieſt, and then came to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and was a Curate at <hi>Berking,</hi> and ſince is gone to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> again. This <hi>Berry</hi> I found a poor zealous Man, whoſe Zeal was far beyond his Knowledg, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:101573:19"/>he fell upon me to come over to their Church; and he brought me acquainted with Mr. <hi>Langworth</hi> a Jeſuit, who ſince is dead, as he the ſaid <hi>Berry</hi> hath told me, and with Mr. <hi>John Keins</hi> a great Jeſuit, and one Mr. <hi>Morgan</hi> a Jeſuit, that lived with the Lord <hi>Powis</hi> in the Year 1676, 1677, 1678. till the Plot was diſcovered; where he is now I know not.</p>
            <p>I was by <hi>Langworth</hi> reconciled to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> he was then <hi>Confeſſarius</hi> to the Ld <hi>Petre</hi> and his Family; and upon my being recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled, I was brought to Mr. <hi>Strange</hi> the then Provincial of their Order, who admitted me into the Society of Jeſus: when I was admitted, it was reſolved by the Jeſuits that I ſhould paſs the time of my Novitiate abroad in diſpatching Buſineſs for the Society, which I chearfully accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and therefore accordingly they provided for me. When I had paid Mr. <hi>Luke Roch,</hi> Commander of the <hi>Biſcay</hi> Merchant, Earneſt for my Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to <hi>Bilboa,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Strange,</hi> then Provincial of the Order, gave me 100 Piſtols for my Supply, in order for my Paſſage into <hi>Spain,</hi> and for my neceſſary Expences there, and ordered me what Money I ſhould need, exhorting me to be as good a Husband as I could, for they had great Occaſions for Money. What Letters they ſent by me I have ſet forth in my Narrative, but when I had got a competent Knowledg of the Deſign, I found <hi>the great Reaſon why they would mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the late King was, becauſe he had deceived them;</hi> and in <hi>Spain</hi> they aſſured me he had been reconciled to their Church, and that upon his Reconciliation, the Society in <hi>Spain</hi> had contributed 3000 Piſtols to his Support, which was paid in by Father <hi>Courtney,</hi> ſometime Provincial of the Jeſuits in <hi>England.</hi> I ſay ſeveral Letters written to one Father <hi>Knot,</hi> in which <hi>the late King did teſtify his Zeal for the Catholick Religion, and promiſed to reſtore it whenever he ſhould come to the Enjoiment of his Right in</hi> England; and that till he had an Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to do it, they ſhould have all the Connivance in the World; and if the Caſe ſhould be ſo hard with him when he came to the Crown, that he could not bring about his Deſires to make their Religion to be the Religion of the Government, yet they ſhould have an Indulgence that ſhould be equivalent, however they ſhould not be excluded out of Offices and Employments under him, and that <hi>they had his Heart and Soul.</hi> When I found the late King not inclined to believe that he was to he murdered, I did in private tell him theſe things, and that the only reaſon why they did deſign to take away his Life, was, becauſe that he had made ſuch Promiſes to them, and aſſured them he was
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:101573:19"/>theirs, and that he was reconciled to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> when beyond Sea, as I had ſeen by his own Letters. <hi>The King commanded me to take no notice of his being reconciled to the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>and declared to me upon the World of a King, that now he did believe they had a Deſign to murder him, acknowledging be had written thoſe Letters I had intimated to his Majeſty;</hi> and withal told me, if I had come to him privately and acquainted him with the Plot, he could of himſelf have daſhed it, and though I deſigned well, yet the Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of it had created a Jealouſy in the People of him.</p>
            <p>Then I acquainted him with his Letters to the Nuns of <hi>Ghent,</hi> when he borrowed Money of them, which they waited for ſeveral Years here in <hi>England:</hi> now he in that Letter did declare to them he would reſtore their Religion when he came to his Right, and that was ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Reaſon that provoked the Party againſt him; and that <hi>St. Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, a French Jeſuit, had a hand in the Murder of</hi> Killigrew's <hi>Man, when he lay upon the Couch in his Majeſty's Cloak.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the King interrupted me, and commanded me to take no farther notice of that Buſineſs, declaring he knew more than I could tell him in that Affair of <hi>Killigrew</hi>'s Man; but withal again repeated the great Jealouſy the People had of him, and that it was much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed by ill Men, that did labour to poſſeſs Peoples Minds againſt him, and ſaid, unleſs an extraordinary Care were taken, the <hi>Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Party would rebel,</hi> and very much inveighed againſt the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> and thought himſelf in as much danger from them, as from the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Party.</p>
            <p>That upon the Diſcovery of ſeveral Papers found about <hi>January,</hi> 167 8/9, at one <hi>Jolliff</hi> a Taylor's, I did obſerve that the late King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt (unleſs his Hand was counterfeited) had commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſeveral Iriſh to riſe; and withal I ſaw Inſtructions given to them to give the Engliſh no Quarter: and I ſaw a Letter of his to a Titular Biſhop, the Biſhop of <hi>Caſſal,</hi> as near as I can remember, wherein he promiſed his Catholick Subjects, that if he were driven through the Neceſſity of Affairs to cauſe a Ceſſation of Arms, it ſhould not be for the Diſadvantage of his Iriſh Catholick Subjects, but to let them have a little time to breathe, in that they might the better be able to ſerve him and themſelves againſt the factious Engliſh there: all which were carried to <hi>White-Hall,</hi> and what became of thoſe Papers then, I know not.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:101573:20"/>
            <p>I ſaw in thoſe Papers ſeveral Paſſes given to thoſe of the Rebels that fled out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> upon the reducing of that Country, wherein they ſhed much of Proteſtant Blood: theſe were recommended by King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, to ſeveral Miniſters of the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> as Perſons that had eminently ſerved his Father in reducing their Country to the Obedience of the Catholick Church, and had contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted much to the deſtroying the Engliſh Hereticks that had planted themſelves in that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Theſe things I intimated to the King, and thought to have diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them to the Parliament; but the King told me that it would ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Malice, and that my Silence of theſe things would intitle me to his Favour, and that I ſhould never want. Beſides all this, his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> did engage me whenever I met with any thing that might reflect upon the King, I would be ſparing there, becauſe the Publication of thoſe things might tend to alienate the King's Heart from the frequent uſe of Parliaments, without which the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom would never rid it ſelf from the apparent Danger of Popery.</p>
            <p>I do further declare that the Jeſuits did tell me that <hi>the coming over of the Princeſs</hi> Henrietta, <hi>was in order to the making way for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring the Catholick Religion here in</hi> England; and that the Breach of Peace with the Dutch was by them contrived, and by the late King conſented to, in order to reduce thoſe States to the Catholick Faith; and that it was thought fit to begin the publick Exerciſe of the Romiſh Religion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to grant a General Toleration here; in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to which, 1600 Prieſts of all Orders, and of divers Nations were ſent over, and moſt of them were kept here on a Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainance for ſecret Service, and others by the then Duke of <hi>York</hi> in half-pay, as disbanded Officers: but this being all defeated by Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, they were much irritated againſt the King. And furthermore the Jeſuits acquainted me that the late King had diſpatched an Envoy to the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> to engage him in the Catholick League, for that <hi>now the Catholick Princes of</hi> Europe <hi>were fully reſolved to extirpate the Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and that the French King, his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and his R. Highneſs the D. of <hi>York, were Heads of this League,</hi> which League his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain</hi> had not carefully obſerved, but gave way to his impertinent Parliaments; but that they might not hinder this good Deſign, the French King had agreed to the Requeſt of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:101573:20"/>his then Royal Highneſs the D. of <hi>York</hi> of remitting 300000 <hi>l. per annum</hi> for 3 Years, if by any means the late King might be diſpatched out of the way, there being <hi>no truſt to be put in him,</hi> that was not only unfaithful in all his Promiſes and Oaths made to them the ſaid Jeſuits and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, but was <hi>an Apoſtate from the Catholick Religion, and therefore not to be endured any longer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Negotiation was carried on by the Lord <hi>Powis,</hi> the late Earl of <hi>Berkſhire,</hi> and <hi>Coleman,</hi> and <hi>St. Germaine,</hi> all which I communicated to his Majeſty in private in the Prince's Lodgings in <hi>Whitehall;</hi> who gave me Thanks for not communicating theſe things to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and told me that he was fully convinced now of the Reaſons and Grounds the Papiſts had of taking away his Life: and the Prince ſaid, I pray God your Majeſty continue in that Opinion, for now you may ſee that they are a ſort of People not to be endured in a Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Good God, ſaid the King, is this the Kindneſs that is to be ſhewed me for all the Favours I have ſhewed that People? At which his Majeſty wept: This was in the Month of <hi>January</hi> 167 8/9, or <hi>Febru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prince then bad me withdraw; and ſent for me the next day, and conjured me not to communicate one word of the Diſcourſe I had with the King: for, faith he, it will neither be ſafe for the King, nor you, nor any of us, if this ſhould be reported. Of which In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction the Prince heartily repented, and ſo did I of my Promiſe; which I have now publiſhed, to undeceive my Countrey in their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they had of the late King.</p>
            <p>His late Majeſty did ever favour the Popiſh Intereſt, as being the greateſt Favourers of Monarchy, though I have ſaid that Popery and a Common-wealth were reconcilable, and often would inſtance the Republiques of <hi>Venice</hi> and <hi>Genoa:</hi> At which his Majeſty ſaid, that there were the Footſteps of Monarchy even in thoſe Republiques. But above all, I found his Majeſty very zealous of reconciling me to the Popiſh Intereſt; and told me, that if I would engage to him upon the Word of a Miniſter not to bear any Teſtimony againſt thoſe I had accuſed before the Council, but would be ruled by him, I ſhould have 10000 <hi>l.</hi> to buy me an Annuity, or a Free-Eſtate; and if I would, I ſhould retire to any College in either Univerſity, and live there quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; urging to me that a Parliament would never gratify me, and it was in his Power only to ſhew me Favour; and therefore adviſed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:101573:21"/>me to be directed by him, and it would be impoſſible for me to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry. To this I thus reply'd; I humbly thank your Majeſty for your Grace and Favour; and I ſhould willingly accept of your Royal Offer were it not the higheſt Breach of Truſt repoſed in me by your Majeſty's Commons in this Parliament: Beſides, Sir, ſaid I, your No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in the Houſe of Peers will, and all Mankind, judg me the worſt of Men if I ſhould ſo baſely deſert my Cauſe: It's plainly proved that the Popiſh Party have a Deſign againſt your Majeſty's Life, and all our Lives, Liberties and Religion; therefore by the Grace of God I will ſtand by the Cauſe to the utmoſt of my Power, to the laſt Minute of my Life.</p>
            <p>The late King did in the Month of <hi>November</hi> 1678, in Mr. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary <hi>Coventry</hi>'s Lodgings, offer me the Biſhoprick of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> and withal promiſed me his Favour of advancing me if I would deſiſt the Enterprize, as he called the Diſcovery of the Popiſh Plot; aſſuring me then that it would not be for his Service, becauſe of the Heat it would put the People into: and farther told me, that the Parliament would forſake me, and not do any thing for me; and if I had a thought of complying with him, I ſhould meet him at the Prince's Lodgings. But I went to the Prince, and told him what his Majeſty had ſaid; who when he had heard of it, <hi>The poor Man</hi> (ſaid the Prince) <hi>doth court his own Ruine the moſt of any Man I know;</hi> and adviſed me not to meddle nor make with any thing of that nature: for, ſaith the Prince, either <hi>he will cheat and expoſe you,</hi> or if he be real, there is an old Wife in the Caſe, who will be ſet on you to draw you off from the good Work you have begun, or perhaps which is worſe.</p>
            <p>I do farther declare, That whereas I have accuſed the Lord <hi>Powis,</hi> the Lord <hi>Bellaſis,</hi> the Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> of <hi>Warder,</hi> the late Lord <hi>Petre,</hi> the late Lord <hi>Stafford,</hi> I did nothing but what became a good Chriſtian to Almighty God, and a good Subject to my Prince, and a good Engliſh-man to my Countrey; for what I have ſaid or ſworn of thoſe Lords is the Truth, and nothing but the Truth, as I ſhall anſwer before God another day: the ſame I declare of all my Evidence I gave in to the King and Council, and to the two Houſes of Parliament.</p>
            <p>And I do declare to all the World, That I have not in the leaſt directly or indirectly, for the hopes of Gain, or any other
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:101573:21"/>Reaſon inducing me thereunto, ſpoken any thing of any Man that I charged to be guilty of the Popiſh Plot, but thoſe who were guilty; and thoſe againſt whom I bore Teſtimony at the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> or at the <hi>King's-Bench</hi> Court, I ſwore nothing but what was true. This I declare as I ſhall anſwer it before God in the next World.</p>
            <p>And whereas it hath been reported by the <hi>Popiſh Party,</hi> and publiſhed by <hi>Roger L'Eſtrange</hi> in his Pamphlet called <hi>the Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> that I ſwore againſt the Jeſuits becauſe they would not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to be of their Society; I do declare that that Order did receive and admit me a Jeſuit, and that they were always the moſt obliging Perſons to me in the World till they found that I had diſcovered thoſe vile Deſigns of Murdering the late King, and Subverting the Proteſtant Religion and Government as by Law eſtabliſhed both in Church and State: and though maliciouſly they did and do ſtill aver I was never admitted Doctor of Divinity at <hi>Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manca,</hi> I do declare ſolemnly to all the World I was admitted Doctor of Divinity at the ſaid Univerſity of <hi>Salamanca,</hi> and did all my Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe for the ſaid Degree that was required of me.</p>
            <p>The Enemies of the Proteſtant Religion have endeavoured to blaſt me with many infamous Crimes, to render me uſeleſs in my Teſtimony relating to the Popiſh Plot, the Grand Adverſary <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger L'Eſtrange</hi> being ready to print in his vile Pamphlet the <hi>Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> any thing that might tend to my Diſadvantage: But I bleſs God I was never ſly in my Converſation, ſo that the ſeveral Lies by him printed have been detected, and Gainſayers ſilenced.</p>
            <p>I thought it not inconvenient to let the World know, that <hi>the late King was a mortal hater of Parliaments;</hi> for in his Letter to the French King, bearing date in <hi>June</hi> 1676, he wrote thus:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>That if he could be aſſured of a Penſion that might conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, he ſhould not continue that way of Governing, <hi>(viz.)</hi> by <hi>frequent Parliaments, which at the beſt was but a clamorous Rabble that took upon them to direct Kings;</hi> but as he was reſolved to be like his Neighbours in Riches and Grandieur, ſo he was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be like them in Religion too.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:101573:22"/>
            <p>This was the Effect and Purport of that Letter, a Copy of which was ſhewed me by <hi>John Keynes</hi> and <hi>Baſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Langworth;</hi> but, ſaid <hi>Keynes,</hi> the French King was too old to be cullied out of his Money by a Man that was ſo uncertain.</p>
            <p>I do in the laſt place declare, That <hi>I am ready to ſeal with my Blood the Truth of my Evidence</hi> that I have given in relation to the Subſtantial Part, and Circumſtantial Parts thereof. I have done no Man wrong that I have charged; and as I have done Right to the World in relation to the Popiſh Plot, ſo I proteſt I did diſcharge a good Conſcience in the Diſcovery of that <hi>Vile Sham,</hi> called <hi>the</hi> Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford-<hi>Plot,</hi> for which poor <hi>Colledg</hi> was baſely murdered there in a form of Law and Juſtice, and that I look on as the worſt of Murders. I renounce all Anarchical Levelling Principles, and deteſt all the Practices of thoſe who have held and maintain'd thoſe Principles, I judging them as dangerous to our Engliſh Monarchy as Popery is to the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>All this I declare, together with my Narrative that is printed, to be true.</p>
            <div type="attestation">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>April</hi> 29, 1685.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>I declare I have ſigned every Page of theſe Papers, with the Day and Year above-written, in the Preſence of Sir <hi>Robert Thomas</hi> Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, <hi>John Arnold</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> and <hi>John Dutton-Colt</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> and the ſame Day I delivered it to them.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Titus Oates.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>April</hi> 29, 1685.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:101573:22"/>
            <p>TO this foregoing Narrative I ſhall now ſubjoin Copies of ſeveral of Dr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Letters to King <hi>Charles</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> the Second, and to divers of the Miniſters of State in that time, and of his Petition to King <hi>Charles;</hi> and ſubmit it to the Reader's Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether his undaunted, and never to be ſhaken Stedfaſtneſs in adhering to and avowing the Truth of his Diſcovery, his plain Dealing with thoſe Princes, his gallant Reſiſtance of the higheſt Temptations, and his juſt Regard to the Intereſt and Rights of his Countrey, and to the brave Aſſetors thereof, all which are before made evident, did not equal the unparallel'd Tortures and heavy Oppreſſion, under which he ſo long groan'd, and from which he had no proſpect, and very little hope of Deliverance.</p>
            <p>Now let the Reader reflect upon the two firſt of theſe Letters, and wonder if he can, when he finds the Doctor thrown off by King <hi>Charles;</hi> I do not ſay when he ſees him out of his Favour, for he never had it: but, as it appears by the foregoing Rerlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Troubles, what he there gained; ſo, I ſhall here obſerve what he loſt, and both by his uncorruptible Integrity. This can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done but by beginning (where he began) at his firſt Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very: That no way pleaſed the King, nor could it; for it ſpoil'd a well-laid Plot, to which he was no Stranger, (ſave to that part which touch'd his Life); therefore, that he might ſtand as far as poſſible out of the reach of Suſpicion, he diſſembles himſelf alarm'd, preſſes the ſearching the Plot to the bottom, appoints <hi>Mock-Faſts,</hi> and what not; and as to the Doctor, aſſigns him an Apartment in <hi>Whitehall,</hi> allows him daily a Table of ſix Diſhes, Wine, and every thing proportionable, and alſo 40 <hi>s. per</hi> Week. This was continued till <hi>April</hi> 1679, then (beſides the 40 <hi>s.</hi>) his Allowance was changed to 10 <hi>l. per</hi> Week, which he received till <hi>Midſummer</hi> 1680, when a ſtop was put to the Paiment thereof. But in <hi>November</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, upon the Addreſs of the Houſe of Lords, the King gave him 200 Guinea's for his Arrears, and ordered him the Allowance of 10 <hi>l. per</hi> Week, which was conſtantly paid till the Diſſolution of the <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi>-Parliament; at which time the King taking a Reſolution not to be further troubled with <hi>unuſeful and dangerous Parliaments,</hi> (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:101573:23"/>ever the fawning Addreſſers pretended to think) together with the Parliament, threw off the Doctor, and the Popiſh Plot, and (taking Sir <hi>Roger</hi> to his aid) made another much more grateful to him; in which, having ſerved the Intereſt of the French King and his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as long as they had occaſion for him, he himſelf at length was removed as uſeleſs.</p>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:101573:23"/>
               <head>A Copy of Dr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Letter to King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, <hi>Nov. 10. 1678.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>May it pleaſe Your Majeſty,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Underſtand by Mr. <hi>Rogers,</hi> that it hath been reported to Your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, that I ſhould in a certain Company, declare that your Majeſty <hi>was a Papiſt,</hi> and that your Majeſty was reſolv'd to order Mr. Attorney-General to proceed againſt me for thoſe Words that were reported to your Majeſty to be ſpoken by me, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Your Majeſty had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>ever ſince your eſcape from</hi> Worceſter; which I hope your Majeſty will not do for your own Honours ſake: For your Majeſty knows that to be true, that <hi>you were reconciled to the Church of</hi> Rome, by Father <hi>Richard Huddliſton,</hi> that was Uncle to <hi>John Huddli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton,</hi> who is excepted in all your Majeſty's Proclamations that are iſſued out againſt Papiſts and Prieſts. And alſo, it's not unknown to ſome, that <hi>Your Majeſty receiv'd the Sacrament according to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage of the Church of</hi> Rome, in the Dutcheſs of <hi>Portſmouth</hi>'s Lodgings, by the Hands of Father <hi>Ireland,</hi> and I my ſelf ſerved then at Maſs; which I have not made Publick, becauſe I would preſerve your Majeſty's Reputation. And what Care your Majeſty took of the Jeſuits when St. <hi>Omers</hi> became ſubject to the French King by Conqueſt (as Men on whom the Hopes of <hi>England</hi> did depend) in your Letter to the French King's Governour, hath not been made ſo publick as I muſt make it, if your Majeſty conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue your Reſolution to have me proſecuted: As alſo the Gracious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe you made to your Royal Siſter of reſtoring the Catholick Religion; and not only that, but the moſt Gracious Memorial your Majeſty put in to the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> by your Envoy there. Your Majeſty may judg that the Statute made in the Thirteenth Year of your Reign, was only made to bridle the Tongues of your People, that they ſhould not dare to ſay you were a Papiſt; but Sir, give me leave to tell your Majeſty, that there was ſomething elſe deſigned in that Act than is there expreſſed; for the late Earl of <hi>Clarendon,</hi> then Lord High Chancellor, who was afraid of your declaring your ſelf to be of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> procured that Act to paſs, and that not without Difficulty, on purpoſe to prevent you that you might not declare your ſelf to be of that Communion, well knowing that if you did, it would tend to the breaking all his Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Projects then on foot to ſerve the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> who had mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried his Daughter: So that if I am proſecuted, it's for ſpeaking the Truth (ſuppoſing that I had ſpoke the Words.) But, to undeceive your
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:101573:24"/>Majeſty, I did not ſpeak them; but it was that Fellow <hi>Blood,</hi> who will confeſs to your Majeſty that it was he that ſpoke the Words, on purpoſe for me to ſecond him, and you know <hi>it was by your own Appointment</hi> that he was ſo bold with your Name and Honour in that particular. Sir, I muſt ſay further, hat when I communicated his Traiterous Letter he wrote to me, to Secretary <hi>Coventry,</hi> he was brought before that Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and confeſſed he wrote the Letter by your Royal Command to lay a Snare for me; and that by your Command he did ſay the Words that <hi>you were reconciled to the Church of</hi> Rome: And when this came to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly talked of, <hi>Blood</hi> was children by your Majeſty, and went off with the ſorrowful Preſent of 500 Guineas, given him by your Majeſty, as a mark of your Royal Diſpleaſure, for ſuch unhand ſome Carriage to your Majeſty, and for ſuch a Knaviſh Trick he endeavoured to put upon me. I leave it to your Royal Conſideration, and ſhall approve my ſelf,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Sir, Your Majeſty's Faithful and Dutiful Subject, <hi>Titus Oates.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Novemb.</hi> 10. 1678.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Copy of</hi> Dr. Oates<hi>'s Letter to King</hi> Charles II. Oct. 14. 1680.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>May it pleaſe Your Majeſty,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>BY Your Majeſty's Command, Sir <hi>Philip Floyd</hi> was with me, and tells me that your Majeſty takes great Offence at my keeping Company with <hi>Republicans;</hi> at the firſt I did not underſtand who Sir <hi>Philip</hi> meant by <hi>Republicans,</hi> which he was pleaſed to explain to me, they were a ſort of <hi>Diſcontented Men that were Enemies to Monarchy in general, and in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, Enemies to Your Majeſty's Royal Perſon and Government:</hi> I proteſted to him I did not keep Company with any ſuch Perſons, and urged it to him that it would be very ingrateful in me if I ſhould keep Company with Men of thoſe Principles: For, Sir, it's my Judgment, that the Engliſh Monarchy, as eſtabliſhed by Law, is that which not only my ſelf, but all thoſe I converſe withal are for, and not only ſo, but are ready to defend with their Lives and Fortunes. But this is my Misfortune, that becauſe I converſe and heartily join with thoſe that are for <hi>Liberty and Property,</hi> and for the <hi>Old Engliſh Government,</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>Popery and Slavery,</hi> and aſſert the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> with that Courage that becomes Engliſh-men, I and my Friends are judged and deemed, by your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, to be Men aiming at <hi>a Common-Wealth,</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>Monarchy</hi> and your Majeſty's Government. But for my farther Information, I begged of Sir <hi>Philip</hi> to know who they were, and what they were that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:101573:24"/>were thus repreſented to your Majeſty, who was pleaſed to tell me it was Mr. <hi>Jenks his Club</hi> that I did frequent, who met at the <hi>Angel and Crown</hi> in <hi>Threadneedle-ſtreet,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bethel</hi>'s <hi>Club that met at the Queen's-Arms</hi> in <hi>Newgate-ſtreet.</hi> Your Majeſty knows that Mr. <hi>Seely</hi> a Major of the late Protector's Army <hi>hath oft met there by your own Appointment,</hi> tho for other ends than I met with that Club at the <hi>Angel and Crown,</hi> at which Club I have been ſeveral Times, for almoſt theſe two Years laſt paſt; and as I expect to ſee the Face of God, I did neither directly nor indirectly hear any one Word ſpoken againſt your Majeſty's Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that the Major can tell, if he hath the leaſt Grain of Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and Truth left in him. <hi>Your Majeſty knows the end of his coming, and we found him out at laſt to be put upon us to abuſe us to your Majeſty:</hi> But bleſſed be God, we never gave any juſt Occaſion to merit that Penſion your Majeſty was pleaſed to order him for ſo great a piece of Service as to be <hi>a Spy</hi> upon a Dozen or Twenty Honeſt Men, that met together to ſpend one Hour, after they had been wearying themſelves in their Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings all the Day, and their Diſcourſe uſually hath been nothing but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Common Things; that Major <hi>Seely</hi> doth indeed loſe his Time, and ſpends your Majeſty's Bounty to very little purpoſe: For our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation is ſo innocent that we are not afraid of ten <hi>Seely</hi>'s or ten <hi>Butlers,</hi> they might freely come and hear what paſſeth amongſt us, were they not Perſons ſo infamouſly Scandalous, that it would be enough to have a Man's Credit queſtioned upon the <hi>Exchange,</hi> to be ſeen with them. But I ſhall ſay no more of them, they being <hi>Your Majeſty's Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Spies</hi> upon ſeveral Honeſt Men in the City. In a Word, I freely own to your Majeſty that I do oft meet with that Club, of which Mr. <hi>Jenks</hi> is a Member, at the <hi>Angel</hi> and <hi>Crown,</hi> and alſo thoſe that meet with Mr. <hi>Bethel,</hi> at the <hi>Queen's-Arms</hi> in <hi>Newgate-ſtreet,</hi> and alſo ſeveral Gentlemen at the <hi>King's-Head</hi> at <hi>Chancery-Lane-end:</hi> and if it be their good will to give me the Honour of their Company, I do not find any Arguments that Sir <hi>Philip</hi> hath uſed, will either prevail with me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain thoſe Companies, or the Character <hi>Seely</hi> may have given to your Majeſty of them, or any of them, ſhall perſwade me to believe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of them than that they are Honeſt Worthy Gentlemen, that ſtudy to ſerve your Majeſty and their Countrey. I know Sir <hi>Philip</hi> to be a very Ill Man, and therefore, having your Majeſty's leave, I thought fit to communicate my Anſwer to your Majeſty in writing; which I humbly ſubmit to your Majeſty, as it becomes your Majeſty's</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Humble Subject and Servant, <hi>Titus Oates.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Octob.</hi> 14. 1680.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:101573:25"/>
               <head>A Copy of Dr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Letter to Sir <hi>Leolin Jenkins,</hi> Secretary of State. <hi>Feb. 22. 1683.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Honourable Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have lain long under his Majeſty's Diſpleaſure, but for what Cauſe to this Day I know not, and am by reaſon of that forbidden the King's Preſence and his Court, which I have obeyed, and have not been at <hi>Whitehall</hi> almoſt theſe three Years (one Time excepted, by Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from their Lordſhips the Commiſſioners of the Treaſury, in <hi>April</hi> or <hi>May</hi> laſt); I have Buſineſs of Importance with the King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, but am unwilling to come leſt I ſhould offend his Majeſty, or receive ſome Affronts, which I cannot well bear: My Requeſt therefore to your Honour is that I may have leave to come, and when I have done my Buſineſs I may depart without being unkindly dealt withal in the Court. So praying your Honour's pardon for this Trouble, I ſhall ſtudy to appear,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Sir, Your Honour's Servant to my poor Power, <hi>Titus Oates.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Copy of a Second Letter from Dr. <hi>Titus Oates,</hi> to Mr. Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary <hi>Jenkins, Feb. 28. 1683.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Honourable Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Gave your Honour the laſt Friday the trouble of a few Lines, in which I told you that I had Buſineſs of Importance with the King and Council; your Anſwer was I muſt apply my ſelf to a Juſtice of the Peace, or to the Courts of Juſtice. The Buſineſs that I had with the Council is a Complaint againſt <hi>Roger L'eſtrange,</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> who in ſeveral Libels of his, called the <hi>Obſervator,</hi> and other Seditious Pamphlets, hath as I humbly conceive, vilify'd and ridicul'd the Diſcovery of the <hi>Popiſh Plot,</hi> and arraigned the Proceedings of the Government upon the ſame: and to give his Libel a Reputation in this his Illegal Courſe, he pretends in one or more of thoſe his Obſervators, that he hath Authority or Leave from ſome of his Majeſty's Miniſters for ſo doing; which I cannot believe. Your Honour knows that his Majeſty was ſo ſenſible of the Danger he was in by reaſon of that horrid Conſpiracy, That <hi>he did not only recommend the ſtrict Examination thereof to his Houſes of Parliament,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:101573:25"/>but alſo was pleaſed to acquaint them how unſafe he was till he ſearched it to the Bottom; beſides this, three Faſts were proclaimed, and kept, which the King himſelf ſtrictly kept, and commanded all his Loving Subjects ſo to do. Several have been Executed, and ſeveral Parliaments have Voted that there was a horrid Helliſh Popiſh Plot.</hi> Now, all theſe Things conſidered, I could never have imagined that any private Perſon would have been ſo bold with the Government, as to uſe ſuch Reflections upon their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, and call in queſtion the Veracity of that Evidence, which was juſtified by his Majeſty's Council, and the Parliaments, and Courts of Juſtice. I though I ſhould never have lived to have ſeen the Day that the Plot ſhould be called in Queſtion, which the King had owned in his ſeveral Proclamations; but ſince it is ſo, I muſt pray your pardon that I cannot apply my ſelf for Redreſs in that way and method your Honour was pleaſed to order; for I humbly conceive that it is the Government that is abuſed, and therefore in Conſcience and Honour it's bound to vindicate its Proceedings from ſuch Aſperſions as are caſt upon them by the ſaid <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> and his Confederates. I would not uſe any method or way to injure the worſt of my Enemies, but hope that the Council will take my hard Uſage from <hi>L'eſtrange,</hi> into ſerious Conſideration, and cauſe him to be Silenced, and Reparation to be made to me. To that end, in this I have ſent a Petition to the King and Council, which I would have preſented my Self, (if I might have had Liberty to appear at Court) in which I pray for Redreſs: I hope God will put it into your Hearts to do me Right. In the mean time,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>SIR, I am your Honour's Humble Servant, <hi>Titus Oates.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Feb.</hi> 28. 1683/4.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>My Humble Requeſt is, That this Petition incloſed may be preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the King and Council, ſo that I may be in ſome probable way of having Redreſs.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:101573:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A Copy of Dr.</hi> Oates<hi>'s Petition.</hi> To the King's Moſt Excellent Majeſty, And to the Right Honourable the Lords, and Others, of His Majeſty's Moſt Honourable Privy Council.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Humble Petition and Complaint of <hi>Titus Oates,</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
               <p>THat your Petitioner, according to his Duty and the Allegiance that he owes, and is alway bound to pay to your Majeſty and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, eſtabliſhed by Law, did in the Month of <hi>September,</hi> in the Year 1678, diſcover a moſt horrid Helliſh <hi>Popiſh Plot,</hi> againſt your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Perſon, the Proteſtant Religion and Government, to the Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of your Majeſty and the then Privy Council; as appears by the ſeveral Proclamations Iſſued out by your Majeſty's Order, with the Advice of your moſt Honourable Council: Which your Petitioner is and will be ready to produce, when thereunto Commanded by your Majeſty.</p>
               <p>That your Majeſty was ſo highly ſenſible of the great Danger your Perſon and your Government were in, by reaſon of that Conſpiracy, that you were Graciouſly pleaſed to proclaim ſeveral <hi>Solemn Faſts,</hi> and Days of <hi>Humiliation;</hi> and did will and require your Loving Subjects to join in hearty Prayer and Supplication with your Majeſty to Almighty God, for a Bleſſing upon the Diſcovery, and for a farther Diſcovery thereof; and in ſeveral of your Majeſty's moſt Gracious Speeches to your Houſes of Parliament, your Majeſty hath been pleaſed to expreſs, how unſafe your Majeſty was till the ſaid Plot was ſearched to the Bottom.</p>
               <p>That ſeveral of the Conſpirators in that Plot were Apprehended and Committed, Indirected and Convicted, and Attained and Executed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Petitioner's Evidence, together with the Evidence of Others, the Attainders of which Conſpirators remain (as your Petitioner believes) upon Record.</p>
               <p>That four ſeveral Parliaments owned the ſaid Diſcovery, and paſſed ſeveral Votes, wherein they did declare that there was <hi>a horrid Popiſh Plot,</hi> for the Deſtruction of your Royal Perſon and your Government, and for the Subverſion of the Proteſtant Religion as by Law eſtabliſhed.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:101573:26"/>
               <p>That <hi>Roger L'eſtrange</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> whom your Petitioner hears is again a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the Peace, (tho turned out for ſeveral Miſdemeanours in the Year 1680) hath defamed and arraigned the Juſtice of the Nation, in ridiculing the ſaid Popiſh Plot, the Diſcovery and Diſcoverers thereof, in a certain Seditious and Scandalous Pamphlet of his, called the <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator,</hi> and in ſeveral other Pamphlets.</p>
               <p>That he, the ſaid <hi>Roger L'eſtrange,</hi> pretends in ſome of thoſe Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and Scandalous Pamphlets, that he is authorized ſo to do by one or both your Secretaries.</p>
               <p>That the ſaid Scandalous and Seditious Pamphlet appears to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance Popery in your Proteſtant Government; and the Popiſh Party hath been much encouraged by the ſame, to revile and threaten your Petitioner.</p>
               <p>That your Petitioner hath born thoſe Scandalous Reflections and Aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, upon the account of his Diſcovery of the ſaid Plot, from the ſaid <hi>L'eſtrange,</hi> theſe four Years with Patience; and had the Scandals only touched your Petitioner, he would not have complained to your Majeſty and this Board; but ſince the ſaid <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> ſcandalouſly vilifies the ſaid Diſcovery, and calls in queſtion the Juſtice of your Government, your Petitioner thinks fit to apply himſelf to your Majeſty and this Board, for Relief.</p>
               <p>The Premiſes conſidered, Your Petitioner humbly prays your Majeſty and this Honourable Board, to relieve him and his Evidence, againſt the Seditious Calumnies of the ſaid <hi>Roger L'eſtrange;</hi> and not ſuffer your Petitioner to be left to be daily Oppreſſed and Deſtroyed, for thoſe Services which your Majeſty and Council, and Parliaments and Courts of Juſtice have owned.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>And Your Petitioner ſhall as in Duty bound, pray for Your Majeſty's Health, and long Life, and happy Reign, <hi>&amp;c. Titus Oates.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:101573:27"/>
               <head>A Copy of Dr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Letter to the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury. March 15. 1683.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>May it pleaſe your Grace,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Having received ſeveral Kindneſſes from you when I was at <hi>Lambeth</hi>-Houſe, do upon that Score think that this may not miſs your Hand, nor I loſe my end in writing at this Time; in which, my Lord, be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to underſtand, that for my own Vindication, I have written to Mr. Secretary <hi>Jenkins,</hi> and in his Letter I have incloſed a Petition and Complaint to the King's moſt Excellent Majeſty, and to the Lords and Others of his Majeſty's moſt Honourable Privy Council, againſt one <hi>Roger L'eſtrange,</hi> who in ſeveral of his Pamphlets called the <hi>Obſervator,</hi> and other Seditious Pamphlets, hath vilified the Diſcovery of the <hi>Popiſh Plot;</hi> and in that, I humbly conceive, he doth arraign and reflect on the Juſtice of the Government: And God having called you to the Great Office of an Arch-biſhop and Privy-Counſellor, I thought my Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to your Grace would not at all be Improper, and therefore I thought I might lay before your Grace the hard uſage I have received from the ſaid <hi>L'etrange</hi> and his Confederate Villains that neither fear God nor reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence Man. Your Grace, I ſuppoſe, hath not forgot that Four <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> did enter upon the Examination both of Witneſſes and Criminals concerned in the Popiſh Conſpiracy; I was the firſt that appeared to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect that Villany, and received the Thanks of the Council, and the Lords in Parliament; and it was looked on as ſuch a piece of Service, that <hi>Your Grace was of the Opinion that ſome Mark of Favour ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on me:</hi> But I was not ſtudious of my own Intereſt, but was always careful (for which I bleſs God) to do my Countrey Juſtice, and have reaped the Fruits thereof, even the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience: And whereas I have been hardly uſed for the Service I did in the Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of that Plot, I think the Government is bound in Honour and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and Juſtice and Truth, to maintain their own Proceedings, and juſtify me from the ſcurrilous Reflections of ſo vile a Fellow as <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> appears to be, in thoſe his Pamphlets. He pretends, in one or two of them, that he hath leave from one or both his Majeſty's <hi>Secretaries</hi> for ſo doing; that I think ought to be reaſon enough for his being ſtopt in his Career and Scribling, and be for ever Silenced, together with Argument of his Fallacy upon the whole Government in that particular: Certainly my Lord, the Church muſt be in a ſad Condition that ſtands in need of <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> for a Supporter; the Religion Eſtabliſhed by Law will be very
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:101573:27"/>contemptible, if <hi>Roger</hi>'s Penny <hi>Obſervator</hi> muſt give it Life. I am ſure our Biſhops have given ſuch Teſtimonies of themſelves and their Power, that there is no need of his ſcurrilous and ſcandalous Pen to maintain their Authority and Reputation. Our Clergy muſt be judged by the Popiſh Party to be Men of little Underſtanding, if they ſtand in need of him to be <hi>their Guide.</hi> Hath he not fallen upon the moſt conſiderable Clergy-men in the City, Men that do not ſtand in need of his Traſh to equip them for the work of the Miniſtry? I dare, by your Grace's leave, be bold to ſay that your Grace, upon Conſideration, will abhor and loath ſuch a Fellow, upon the account of theſe and other Aggravations; and ſeeing I have been uſeful in my Day, I beg your Grace would be inſtrumental in doing me the Juſtice that is due to a Man, a Chriſtian, and a Miniſter of the Church: If I have done any Man wrong let me ſuffer, if I am innocent (as I muſt be accounted till convicted of ſome Enormity or Irregularity) then let me be protected, and not left to be oppreſſed and deſtroyed by my Enemies, for the Services that your Grace hath formerly owned in Council and in Parliament, and likewiſe his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, in ſeveral Proclamations to his People and Speeches to his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. My Lord, I ſhall ſay no more but beg your Grace's Pardon and Bleſſing; and tho I have miſrepreſented to your Grace, I ſhall ſtudy to appear,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
                  <signed>Your Grace's moſt Affectionate Servant, <hi>Titus Oates.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>March</hi> 15. 1683.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>My Lord, I would have waited upon your Grace, but ſince the Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the Parliament at <hi>Oxford,</hi> your Servants have put Affronts upon me (of which I unwillingly take notice). which have hindred my paying my Reſpects to your Grace: And likewiſe I underſtand that ſome Evil Inſtruments, by lies and Falſhood, have endeavoured to leſſen me in your Grace's Affections, which I have patiently born rather than put your Grace and my Self to the unneceſſary trouble of a fruitleſs Vindication of my Innocency.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:101573:28"/>
               <head>A Copy of Dr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Letter to the Biſhop of <hi>London, March 15. 1683.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>WHen the <hi>Popiſh Plot</hi> was firſt diſcovered, <hi>your Lordſhip was very zealous in the proſecuting Popery;</hi> and I have heard you often ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs your hearty good will to root that Faction out of this Nation: <hi>I hope your Zeal for the Proteſtant Religion is not a whit abated;</hi> yet my Hopes are not without ſome Fears, when I have it by ſome reported (though I cannot give full Credit to it) that your Lordſhip, together with the Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> do maintain <hi>R. L'eſtrange,</hi> and encourage him in that vile Pamphlet called the <hi>Obſervator,</hi> in which your Lordſhip may ſee the Juſtice of the Nation is arraigned; and, by Conſequences of his own drawing, the Blood of thoſe that were executed upon the account of the Popiſh Conſpiracy, charged upon the Government; and I do not find him lie under any Cenſure for that his vile Libel, by your Lordſhip, under whoſe Jurisdiction he is: Is the Church in ſo low a Condition that ſhe ſtands in need of <hi>Roger</hi>'s Support? Is the Government in ſuch a ſtate as none can cure it but he? Is Epiſcopacy at ſuch a point that it cannot be brought to its Priſtine State without him? Is the Miniſtry of the Church in ſuch Contempt that none but he, by his Penny-Obſervator, can reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver its Reputation and Credit? How is all this done? by Seditious, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious, Scurrilous Lies; by encouraging Popery, by reviling the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Intereſt, by arraigning the Juſtice of the Nation, by villifying the Diſcovery of the Popiſh Plot, and endeavouring to expoſe the Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers (by a heap of infamous Lies) to the Nation, as Impoſtors.</p>
               <p>My Lord, I am a Miniſter, yea a Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>have done her more Service than any Clergy-man in England;</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I hate thoſe Monſters that are amongſt us who were bred in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, and have left this Religion and are reconciled to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and are by that means declared <hi>Traytors</hi> by our Law, I am looked upon by our <hi>little Clergymen,</hi> as a <hi>Diſſenter</hi> from the Church of <hi>England:</hi> But my Lord, your Lordſhip hath, I hope, better Thoughts of me; tho I am grieved to hear your Lordſhip ſhould be concerned for a vile Obſervator, that hath been ſo profuſe as to call in Queſtion the Truth of the Popiſh Plot, of which your Lordſhip was convinced and ſatisfied; and for the farther Diſcovery of which you were ſo diligent in Parliament and Council, in your Examination both of Criminals and Witneſſes. I purpoſe to be heard in Council againſt this <hi>L'eſtrange;</hi> in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:101573:28"/>order thereunto I have written to Mr. Secretary <hi>Jenkins,</hi> and in that Letter I have incloſed a Petition and Complaint againſt him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am an humble Suitor to your Lordſhip to do me Right, and help me to my intended Hearing; and if I cannot be heard, I muſt print my Caſe, which you know is an appealing to the People, which ſome have not liked; But what muſt I do? I have born his ſcandalous Reflections ſo long that I can bear no longer; and I conceive, as I am a Miniſter, I ought to have been protected by the Biſhops and Prelates of the Church, in whoſe Communion I am, though I have been miſrepreſented by <hi>L'eſtrange</hi> and others of his Confederates, therefore as your Lordſhip tenders the Juſtice and Honour of the Government, I hope you will not only diſcountenance the vile Uſage of me by <hi>L'eſtrange,</hi> but alſo endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that he may be ſilenced; for its he and thoſe of his Crew that have created ſuch Animoſities amongſt the King's Leige People. It hath been the Policy of the Synagogue of <hi>Rome</hi> to divide Proteſtants, and he is the Tool they make uſe of to divide us: There hath ſcarce been any one Sober Clergy-man of Note that hath eſcaped his Laſh; and what credit the Church can have by ſuch an Elf I cannot conceive. My Lord, I will not detain you any longer, but I ſhall only proteſt my Intergrity and Truth in what I have done, in reference to the Popiſh Plot; and I have had your Lordſhip's good word in that particular, and queſtion not but upon Conſideration your Lordſhip will be a means of having Right done me in my Complaint. 'Tis true I lie under the King's Diſpleaſure, for what I know not to this Day; I thank God I am not conſcious to my ſelf of any thing that I have ſaid or done that might have done him any prejudice: if I have, I ſhould be glad to underſtand my Error, that I might make Reparation. In a Word, I ſhall ſtudy to appear,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
                  <signed>Your Lordſhip's Obedient Servant, <hi>Titus Oates.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>March</hi> 15. 1683.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Copy of</hi> Dr. Oates<hi>'s Letter to King</hi> Charles II. April 12. 1684.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>May it pleaſe Your moſt Excellent Majeſty,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Thought it my duty, for the honour of Truth, to whom all Men are Debtors, and for my own Vindication, to apply my ſelf to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Miniſters and Counſellors, for redreſs againſt the ſcurrilous Pamphlets of <hi>Roger L'eſtrange,</hi> in which I find the Juſtice of your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's Government arraigned, for the Service I did in the Diſcovery of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:101573:29"/>the <hi>Popiſh Plot.</hi> I am expoſed by him and his Confederates to the Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of thoſe Men that carried on the Conſpiracy againſt your Royal Perſon and Government, but from them I could have no redreſs, tho as I humbly conceive, that the proper way for me to proceed, conſidering the nature of my Complaint, and the Circumſtances under which I now am. <hi>Your Majeſty, when this Popiſh Plot was firſt diſcovered, was highly ſenſible of the danger your Perſon was in by reaſon of that Conſpiracy, ſo that you were pleaſed to preſs your Parliaments to examine it to the bottom,</hi> and not only ſo, but in all Humility your Majeſty did addreſs your ſelf to the Majeſty on High, and commanded all your Loving Subjects to join with your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty in hearty and humble Supplication to Almighty God our Heavenly Father, to give a Bleſſing to the then Diſcovery of the Popiſh Plot, and to make a farther Diſcovery thereof, and <hi>no Man but a Papiſt will judg any otherwiſe of your Majeſty, but that you were in earneſt.</hi> None Sir, I ſay, but ſuch will ſo much as conceive you called <hi>Mock-Faſts;</hi> hence it is that thoſe Blaſphemous Cut-throats did compare you to <hi>Ahab,</hi> as I can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in one of their Pamphlets. And beſides all this, Sir, <hi>Your Majeſty hath been pleaſed to tell your Loving Subjects how fully you were ſatisfied</hi> in the reality of the Deſigns of the Popiſh Party, and their Abettors, againſt your Perſon and Government, but by what means it is not yet known that Men have taken the boldneſs to arraign your Government, and charge the Blood of thoſe Jeſuits and other Traitors that ſuffered in that Cauſe, upon you and the Government; eſpecially <hi>Roger L'eſtrange,</hi> who hath abuſed the Diſcoverers and Diſcovery of the <hi>Popiſh Plot:</hi> And in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Libel called the <hi>Obſervator,</hi> he, as I humbly conceive, hath taken a great deal of pains to perſwade the Nation that there was no Popiſh Plot, but that it was a meer Fiction; the Conſequence of which I leave your Majeſty to draw: Certainly it will be ſo foul a Conſequence that a Loyal Heart muſt tremble to conſider it. I ſhould not have trotbled your Majeſty had your Miniſters taken my Complaint into Conſideration, and tho I was not thought worthy of being heard by them, yet by their leaves, I humbly conceive, your Majeſty's Proceedings have been ſo juſt and good in the executing of thoſe that were in that Helliſh Conſpiracy, that they deſerve to be vindicated from theſe foul Aſperſions caſt upon them by <hi>Roger L'eſtrange</hi> and his Popiſh Crew; and altho, by unjuſt Reports and Miſrepreſentations, I am out of your Majeſty's Favour, yet I may ſay <hi>if</hi> Oates <hi>had not been Loyal, your Majeſty had not been in the Land of the Living,</hi> whatever the Popiſh Crew have ſuggeſted in their ſcurrilous Pamphlets againſt me, for diſcovering their impious Deſigns againſt your Majeſties Perſon and the Proteſtant Religion. I ſent a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition to Mr. Secretary <hi>Jenkins</hi> but could not be heard, and I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:101573:29"/>to ſeveral of your Council, but can have no Effects of my juſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, though I am left to ſtarve; yet I may ſay I have deſerved better of the Government than to live in danger of being knockt of the Head as I go along the Streets, and for no other Crime, but that of the 28th and 29th of <hi>September</hi> 1678; if I muſt periſh for ſerving your Majeſty and the Government, I humbly pray that I may periſh quietly, and ſtarve in Peace, and not be put into a Bear's Skin in order to be worried to Death by Popiſh Dogs, whoſe Religion is nothing elſe but a Ciſtern of Immorality, and their Immorality Treaſon in the higheſt Degree: Therefore let any Man ſhew me a Papiſt, and I can ſhew a Man that is, or muſt (when commanded by his Prieſt) be <hi>a Traitor; eſpecially ſuch a Papiſt who hath been bred and inſtructed in the Proteſtant Religion, and is recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to the Synagogue of</hi> Rome, <hi>ſuch a Papiſt I hate, and I truſt in God to ſee ſuch ruined, unleſs that Vengeance be prevented by timely Repentance.</hi> None, Sir, hath been uſed like me, and this <hi>L'eſtrange hath as I am informed threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to write againſt me till he hath writ me out of the World;</hi> what the meaning is of ſuch an Expreſſion I humbly leave to your Majeſty to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. I have in this incloſed a Petition to your Majeſty, and queſtion not but you will be graciouſly pleaſed to take my ſad Caſe into ſerious Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. Sir, from my Heart and Soul I love your Majeſty, and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment eſtabliſhed by Law; and have, I am ſure, given your Majeſty as great Demonſtration of my Loyalty and Duty, as any one Subject you have in your three Kingdoms, and therefore be pleaſed to give me leave to put your Majeſty in mind of the ſad Fate of <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> the late King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and how his Ruine was brought about; your Majeſty knows the Story better than I can expreſs it, and a Word is enough to ſo wiſe a Prince as your Majeſty hath appeared to be. I will not trouble your Majeſty any farther, but that God the King of Kings may bleſs your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty with a long Life and a happy Reign over us, is and ever ſhall be the daily Prayer of,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>SIR, Your Majeſty's moſt Dutiful, Loyal, and Obedient Subject and Servant, <hi>Titus Oates.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>London, April</hi> 12. 1684.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:101573:30"/>
               <head>A Copy of Dr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Letter to King <hi>James</hi> the Second, <hi>Aug. 12. 1688.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>May it pleaſe Your Majeſty,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have no Friend that can attend your Majeſty with my Petition, or elſe I ſhould not have made my Application to you in this Way, it not being uſual for Subjects to addreſs themſelves in ſuch a Manner to their Prince; Neceſſity drives me to it, for contrary to all Law and Humanity, I am miſerably oppreſſed by Mr. <hi>Ellis the Marſhal of your Priſon of the King's-Bench,</hi> who hath within a few Years laſt paſt decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelf to be of the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> upon which, together with his Authority, I humbly conceive he takes Liberty thus to oppreſs me, to revenge himſelf and thoſe of that Communion upon me: He kept my Servant from me, tho it's well known, that by reaſon of my long and miſerable Impriſonment, I am lame and not able to help my ſelf. He ſtops all People at the Gate from coming at me, by which means I muſt periſh, becauſe no Succour can come at me, unleſs Care be taken by your Majeſty that a ſtop be ſpeedily put to his Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Cruel Uſage of me. I humbly conceive the Cauſes of my Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment do not lie before him: His Buſineſs is to keep me in ſafe Cuſtody, and not to oppreſs me. He demands Ten Guineas of me for <hi>Civility-Money,</hi> which is not his due to receive, nor in my power to pay, for which <hi>he threatens me with Irons;</hi> the Truth is the whole City crys out Shame of his manner of dealing with me, and the more becauſe of his Religion. I am certain thoſe of the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> pretend to more Humanity than any other People, but his Uſage of me ſhews him rather a Turk than a Chriſtian; there will be loud Crys againſt him either at Term or in Parliament for his many Extravagancies in the Execution of his Office: What the Cauſes of his baſe Uſage of me are, I humbly beſeech your Majeſty, may be heard Face to Face before Sir <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Allebone,</hi> or in ſuch a way as your Majeſty ſhall think fit; for at the preſent <hi>I am under great Apprehenſions of being murdered by him,</hi> which you may prevent if you pleaſe. All which is humbly ſubmitted to your Majeſty, by</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your poor Priſoner, <hi>Titus Oates.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Aug.</hi> 12. 1688.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:101573:30"/>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>I am much impaired in my Health, and I have done that which a good Subject ought to do; ſo that if I am murdered my Blood will not lie at my Door, but at their Doors that ſhould do me Juſtice; for <hi>Favour I expect none, nor would I be ſo Ill a Man as to deſire any,</hi> but <hi>I cry aloud for Juſtice, that I may not be murthered,</hi> by a Man who imagines he may do good Service to thoſe of the Romiſh Church, to ruine me while I am in his Cuſtody: Therefore once more I pray for Juſtice.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
            <p>HAving affirmed in the foregoing Tract that both the <hi>Juries</hi> which found Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> guilty, were Men of the ſame <hi>Gang</hi> and <hi>Kidney;</hi> to explain my meaning therein, I ſay, that moſt, if not every of them, were <hi>Diſciples of</hi> L'Eſtrange, and <hi>by conſequence Tories; Children of Paſſive Obedience, Abhorrers of Parliaments, Addreſſers againſt them, Betrayers of Charters,</hi> and <hi>Anti-Excluſioners:</hi> Nor could it poſſibly be otherwiſe, for there was at that day a ſelect Liſt of about 200 ſuch Men, and no others, packt to do the Court's Drudgery; as will evidently appear by reading over the Names of the Grand and Petty-Juries which paſs'd upon the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-to-be-forgotten Lord <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> Alderman <hi>Corniſh,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Gaunt,</hi> in the ſecond Part of the Diſplay of Tyranny: I obſerve there is not found amongſt them one of the Jury which was returned by our <hi>Bethel</hi> and <hi>Corniſh,</hi> and which brought in that honourable <hi>Ignoramus</hi> upon the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment againſt the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury;</hi> and I may well ſay that was in every reſpect the greateſt Jury that was ever returned in <hi>England.</hi> Out of this Liſt were every of the Doctor's 24 Jury-men pickt, and every Man of the firſt Jury were in the Pannels which <hi>North</hi> and <hi>Rich</hi> packt upon my Lord <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> and nine of them were alſo return'd upon Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Corniſh</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Gaunt;</hi> of the ſecond Jury, four were returned upon my Lord <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> Alderman <hi>Corniſh,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Gaunt,</hi> three more up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my Lord <hi>Ruſſel</hi> ſingly, and the other five upon Alderman <hi>Corniſh</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Gaunt;</hi> divers of them actually ſerved on thoſe Juries, and moſt of thoſe who did not, were challenged.</p>
            <p>That I may now ſet the bloody Tragedy of that day in its true light, and ſhew whence this accurſed Practice of packing Juries ſprang, I ſhall tranſcribe a noted <hi>Prediction</hi> of one of the Guides of the hair-brain'd <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: Heraclitus Ridens,</hi> who foretold, ſoon after the unhappy Election of Sir <hi>John Moore</hi> to be Lord-Mayor; that <hi>at or before</hi> 1683, <hi>they ſhould
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:101573:31"/>have Juries for their turn:</hi> And then talking to the <hi>Whiggs</hi> about <hi>Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> told them; <hi>They muſt come to't, and they ſhould come to't.</hi> I conclude with another very remarkable <hi>Propheſy</hi> of the <hi>Guide of the Inferiour Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy;</hi> he at the very Juncture when it was reſolved that <hi>North</hi> and <hi>Rich</hi> muſt be Sir <hi>John Moore</hi>'s Sheriffs, foretold the direful Conſequences thereof, in his <hi>Obſervator</hi> of <hi>May</hi> 20, 1682, <hi>Number</hi> 140, in theſe words: <hi>If it ſhould pleaſe God to ſend us SEASONABLE SHERIFFS, and fair play for O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R MONEY, there are ſet a foot ſo many Titles in competition for the Gallows, that it would be a hard matter to ſettle their Claims, and ſay who ſhould go firſt.</hi> And in his <hi>Obſervator</hi> of <hi>May</hi> 27, 1684. he told us whom he eſteemed his <hi>Seaſonable Sheriffs:</hi> He ſays, <hi>Prithee Whig, wilt thou ſet THEIR</hi> CORNISH <hi>and</hi> BETHEL, <hi>THEIR</hi> PILKINGTON <hi>and</hi> SHUTE, <hi>againſt our</hi> NORTH <hi>and RICH; our</hi> DANIEL <hi>and</hi> DASH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WOOD, and <hi>ſay which of theſe Sheriffs are the likelier Men to juggle Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants out of their Lives?</hi> Had the poor depreſſed <hi>Whig</hi> in that day an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd the Trepaning Tory this enſnaring Queſtion, it had been at the hazard of his Head.</p>
            <p>But now (being warranted by Parliament ſo to do) I ſay that <hi>my Lord</hi> Ruſſel <hi>and Alderman</hi> Corniſh <hi>were barbarouſly murdered,</hi> as was good <hi>Mrs.</hi> Gaunt, <hi>under pretence and colour of Law,</hi> which as my Lord <hi>Ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel</hi> well obſerved <hi>is the worſt ſort of Murder;</hi> and this I think was <hi>jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling Proteſtants out of their Lives</hi> with a witneſs: I alſo ſay, (by the ſame warrant) that <hi>the Proſecution of Dr.</hi> Oates <hi>for Perjury was a Deſign to ſtifle the Popiſh Plot, and that the Verdicts againſt him were corrupt, and the Judgments cruel and illegal;</hi> and all this was accompliſhed by the ſame Set of <hi>Jury-men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus (to gratify Sir <hi>Roger,</hi> to whom I pay no ſmall deference) I have ſet <hi>our</hi> Bethel <hi>and</hi> Corniſh, <hi>our</hi> Pilkington <hi>and</hi> Shute, <hi>againſt their</hi> North <hi>and</hi> Rich, <hi>their</hi> Daniel <hi>and</hi> Daſhwood; and ſhew'd him not only who were the likelieſt Men to <hi>juggle Proteſtants out of their Lives,</hi> but who they were that actually did it; and ſo I bid him adieu.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. L'S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
